<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mirabilia dei, or, Britannia gaudio exultans Opened in a congratulatory sermon for the safe return of our Gracious Soveraign, and happy restitution to the full and free exercise of His royall authoritie. Preached on the 14th. of June, [16]60. which was the day set apart for the members, master, and students of the Kings Colledge, in the town and parish of Old Aberdeen, to commemorat and solemnly praise the Lord for the rich mercies above mentioned: by Alexander Scrougie preacher of the Gospel, and minister at Old Aberdeen.</title>
            <author>Scrogie, Alexander, d. 1661.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 110 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58858</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2127</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R218663</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830235</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830235</idno>
            <idno type="VID">34685</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58858)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 34685)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2019:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mirabilia dei, or, Britannia gaudio exultans Opened in a congratulatory sermon for the safe return of our Gracious Soveraign, and happy restitution to the full and free exercise of His royall authoritie. Preached on the 14th. of June, [16]60. which was the day set apart for the members, master, and students of the Kings Colledge, in the town and parish of Old Aberdeen, to commemorat and solemnly praise the Lord for the rich mercies above mentioned: by Alexander Scrougie preacher of the Gospel, and minister at Old Aberdeen.</title>
                  <author>Scrogie, Alexander, d. 1661.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 35, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by a Society of Stationers,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: title page torn affecting text and imprint.</note>
                  <note>Copy stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  II, --  King of England, 1630-1685 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Sovereign (1660-1685 : Charles II) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:34685:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>MIRABILIA DEI,</hi> OR, BRITANNIA GAUDIO EXULTANS.</p>
            <p>Opened in a Congratulatory Sermon for the ſafe Return of our Gracious Soveraign, and happy Reſtitution to the full and free exerciſe of His Royall Authoritie.</p>
            <p>Preached on the 14<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> of <hi>June,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> which was the day ſet apart for the Members, Maſters, and Students of the <hi>KINGS</hi> Colledge, in the Town and Pariſh of Old <hi>Aberdeen,</hi> to commemorat and ſolemnly praiſe the Lord for the rich mercies above mentioned:</p>
            <p>By <hi>ALEXANDER SCRO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>GIE</hi> Preacher of the Goſpel, and Miniſter at Old ABERDEEN.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 1.</bibl> 
               <hi>The King ſhall joy in thy ſtrength, O Lord, and in thy ſalvation how greatly ſhall he rejoyce.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 6.</bibl> 
               <hi>Now I know that the Lord ſaveth his Anointed.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Prov. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4. 21.</bibl> 
               <hi>Fear thou the Lord and the King: and medle not with them that are given to change.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 Sam. 26. 9.</bibl> 
               <hi>Deſtroy him not; For who can ſtretch forth his hand againſt the Lords Anointed and be guiltleſſe?</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ambroſ.</hi> ad <hi>Scapulam.</hi>
               </bibl> Colimus Imperatorem—ut hominem a Deo ſecundum, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nob.</hi> cont. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>entes,</hi> lib. 8.</bibl> Vo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ethnici conſcios timentes, nos vero con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiam ſolum.</q>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>H,</hi> Printed by a Society of <hi>Stationers.</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:34685:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:34685:3"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable and NOBLE LORD, WILLIAM Earle of <hi>GLENCAIRN,</hi> Lord of <hi>Kilmawers,</hi> &amp;c. Lord High Chancellour of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of SCOTLAND.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD left not mankind in a confuſion like beaſts, but hath appointed a Magiſtracy, by which Policy receives it's order<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Quod Magiſtratus ſunt</hi> (ſaith <hi>Chryſoſt.) Quod</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Chryſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 23. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ad <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> quidem imperant, iſti vero pareant: quod non ſimpliciter at temere cuncta ferunt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r, nec populi fluctuum inſtar, huc at que illuc circumaguntur, Divinae ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiae opus eſſe dico:</hi> and bleſſed be God that hath given ſuch power to men.</p>
            <p>Government is ſo neceſſary, that better no Creation, then no Government: better not to be at all, then not to be under Rule. When there was no King in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> every man did that which was right in his own eyes: <hi>Micah</hi> and his Mother, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate <note place="margin">Judg. 17. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <hi>c.</hi> 18. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 21. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> perſons, made a goodly Image, and had a houſe of gods,
<pb facs="tcp:34685:4"/> 
               <hi>Judg. 17. 4, 5. Gibea</hi> a City, raviſhed the <hi>Levites</hi> Concubine to death, <hi>Judg. 19. 25, 26.</hi> and the Tribe of <hi>Benjamin</hi> counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanced their villanie, <hi>Chap. 20. 13,</hi> &amp;c. The <hi>Danites,</hi> a Tribe robbed and ſet up Idolatry, <hi>Chap. 18. 17, 18. 30. Ubi Princeps non eſt</hi> (ſaith <hi>Athanaſius) ibi prorſus diſturbatio naſcitur,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Athanaſ. in <hi>Orat.</hi> ad ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus idola.</note> Where there is no King, there is nothing but overthrow, confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and trouble.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Of all Governments, <hi>Monarchy</hi> is the beſt: 1. For Antiquity. 2. For Order. 3. For Peace. 4. For Strength. 5. For Stability. It is the beſt, becauſe God ſetled it among his People, and the moſt perfect, being the laſt he eſtabliſhed among them. <note place="margin">
                  <p>See <hi>Juſtin.</hi> in <hi>Orat.</hi> ad gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tes: <hi>Cyprian.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>de idol: vanit.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hieron.</hi> in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. ad <hi>Ruſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum</hi> Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chum.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thom.</hi> in 1. part, 4. 103. <hi>Art. 3. &amp; lib.</hi> 4. cont. gent. <hi>Ariſt. polit. l. 8. c. 10. Plato</hi> in polit.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Plutarch</hi> in <hi>Opuſc.</hi> de Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>hia. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſerm. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> civ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 5. 29.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Kings have their Authority from God, <hi>Rom. 13. 1.</hi> its given them from above, <hi>Joh. 19. 11.</hi> He ſetteth up Kings, <hi>Dan. 2. 21.</hi> and by him they reign, <hi>Prov. 8. 15.</hi> They are Gods Anointed, <hi>1 Sam. 12. 3. 5. 2 Sam. 19. 21. Cujus juſſu naſcun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur homines, ejus juſſu conſtituuntur principes;</hi> by whoſe appointment they be born men, by his appointment (and no other) are they made Princes, ſaith <hi>Iren. lib. 5.</hi> and that is only by God, <hi>Inde illis poteſtas, unde Spiritus,</hi> thence have they their power, whence they have their breath, ſaith <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuli,</hi> Apol. p. 695.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Kingly Government and Authority, is not founded upon ſanctifying Grace, nor is it loſt by ſin, which was the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous error of ſome Hereticks called <hi>Pſeudoapoſtoli,</hi> who as <hi>Bernard</hi> relates, taught <hi>Omnem poteſtatem tam politicam quam Eccleſiaſticam, amitti per peccatum mortale, ac proinde illis; qui mortalis culpae reï ſunt, non eſſe obtemperandum:</hi> Auguſt. ſaith well; <hi>Qui Mario Imperium dedit, ipſe Caio Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſari, qui Auguſto, ipſe &amp; Neroni; qui Veſpaſiano vel Patri vel Filio ſuaviſſim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Imperatoribus, ipſe &amp; Apoſtatae</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liano. All Kings are Gods Anointed, not only <hi>David, 2 Sam. 19. 21. Solomon, 2 Chro. 6. 42. Joſiah,</hi> Lam. 4. 20. but wicked <hi>Saul, 1 Sam. 12. 5. 13.</hi> and <hi>Cyrus</hi> a Heathen, <hi>Iſa. 45. 1.</hi> want of Religion doth not un-make a King, for then <hi>Cyrus</hi> had been no King; nor had their been any King of old, but in <hi>Judah,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:34685:4"/> nor any now, but ſome Chriſtian Kings, and but few of them both too. Tyranny un-makes them not, elſe <hi>Saul</hi> a Tyrant, and perſecuting Emperors had been no Kings. Hereſie un-makes them not, for then <hi>Conſtantius, Valens, Valentinian</hi> the younger, who were Arrians, <hi>Anaſtaſius</hi> an Eutychian, <hi>Heraclius</hi> a Monothelite and others had been no Emperors. Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion diveſts them not of their Authority, for then <hi>Saul</hi> deſerted and excommunicate of God, <hi>1 Sam. 15. 18.</hi> had been no King. Yea, Apoſtaſie it ſelf deprives them not of their Crown; <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> then had been no Emperour: But God acknowledged <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> and <hi>Saul,</hi> and other wicked Kings as his Anointed and Kings: And the Primitive Chriſtians acknowledged and obeyed theſe Hereticall Emperours; yea, and obeyed <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate: No Chriſtian ever enterpriſed or taught, or ſtirred up the Subjects to De-throne them, be their Religion what it will, and themſelves never ſo wicked, they continue Kings, and by God they Reigne. Good Kings, <hi>Per Deum propitium:</hi> wicked ones, <hi>Per Deum iratum,</hi> but ſtill <hi>per Deum,</hi> by God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The perſons of Kings was ſtill accounted Sacred; their Office and Power Sacred, and they reverenced as Gods <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ignat.</hi> Ep. 7. ad <hi>Smyrn. Tertul.</hi> in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polloge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> c. 30. &amp; 33. 37. <hi>Tertulli.</hi> ad <hi>Scapulam.</hi>
               </note> Anointed, that could not lawfully be touched, <hi>1 Sam. 24. 6. 10. 1 Chron. 16. 22. Neque enim rege quiſquam praeſtantior aut quiſquam ei ſimilis in rebus creatis,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ignatius: Rex à Deo primus, poſt Deum ſecundus,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tertul.</hi> He is the ſecond from God, and the firſt after God: count not God, and the King is the firſt, count God, and he is the ſecond. He is <hi>ſolo Deo minor</hi> (ſaith that ſame Author) and <hi>om<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ibus major dum ſolo vero Deo minor eſt:</hi> How ſacred and highly did holy <hi>David</hi> eſteem the perſon of King <hi>Saul,</hi> may appear from <hi>1 Sam. 24. 6, 10, 12, 13.</hi> and <hi>Chap. 26. 9, 10, 11.</hi> and from <hi>2 Sam. 1. 14, 15, 16.</hi> of the heroick reverence of primitive Chriſtians to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their Emperors will a little appear from the next <hi>Section:</hi> Their Writ was ſtiled, <hi>Sacri apices;</hi> their Word, <hi>Divalis Juſſio;</hi> their preſence, <hi>Sacra veſtigia;</hi> their Warrant, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſacra praeceptio, piiſſima Juſſio, juſſum pium</hi> and <hi>pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um decretum;</hi> theſe were the uſual ſtiles of Councels when they ſpoke of them.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:34685:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> So great was the heroick Loyalty of the holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Commanders and Chriſtians in primitive times, that it was Univerſally accounted unlawfull to reſiſt their Emperours by force of Arms, although perſecutors, or hereticall, or apoſtates; not becauſe they wanted force, as <hi>Bellarm.</hi> and others would <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bellarm.</hi> l. 5. de <hi>Rom. Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tif.</hi> c. 6. &amp; 7. <hi>Cyprian.</hi> ad <hi>Demetrian. Tertul.</hi> in <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leget.</hi> c. 37.</note> make the world believe. <hi>Tertull.</hi> and <hi>Cyprian</hi> are living wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes to the contrare. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaith the number of Chriſtians was marvellous great. We do not reſiſt (ſaith he) although our number be great; if we would be revenged, we could not want force, we are viſibly known to you and intereſted in all your Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, Cities, Forts, Decuries,—What war are we not ready and fit for, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſaith <hi>Tertul.</hi> It is clear that the far greater part of <hi>Julians</hi> Army were Chriſtians, as appeared inſtantly upon his death, by their loud Acclamations to <hi>Jovian</hi> his Succeſſor; <hi>Chriſtiani ſumus:</hi> yet they having power did not reſiſt, not though the people be prone to reſiſt you, ſaith <hi>Nazian,</hi> not when <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nazian.</hi> Orat. 2. in <hi>Julian. Ambroſ.</hi> tom. 3. l. 5. poſt. epiſt. 32.</note> the people are preſent and offer a defence, ſaith <hi>Ambroſ.</hi> when the ſame <hi>Ambroſ.</hi> was ſufficiently armed both by power of People and Souldiers, ſtrengthned with the might of Chriſt, and guarded by Angels, yet would not defend his Church with violence againſt the furie of the hereticall Emperour, as wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe <hi>Auguſt. Epiſt. 166. Athanaſius</hi> having ſufficient power to ſtir up the Emperour <hi>Conſtance</hi> a true profeſſor againſt his <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Athanaſ.</hi> in Apollog. ad <hi>Conſtantium.</hi>
               </note> brother <hi>Conſtantius</hi> an Heretick, yet would not, but rather ſubmitted to the violence of perſecution. That famous example of that renowned <hi>Thebean</hi> Legion of 6666. Souldiers, is well known, who having ſufficient force to reſiſt, yet ſuffered them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be ſlain for their Chriſtian profeſſion by the Officers of <hi>Maximinian</hi> the Emperour: multitude of teſtimonies might be produced from Antiquity to clear this to the full, which the narrow compaſſe of an Epiſtle doth forbid. The <hi>Apoſtles</hi> did chooſe rather to ſuffer evil, then to revenge, although endued with the power of working miracles, <hi>Acts 5. 5. 9, 10.</hi> Heroicall Martyrs thought their faith glorified in this, that being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted, yet performed obedience; for conſcience ſake they did it, in obedience to Gods Command, ſaith <hi>Auguſt.</hi> and <hi>Amobius.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:34685:5"/> They thought it more lawfull to be killed, then to kill, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting the Emperour, ſaith <hi>Tertul.</hi> in <hi>Apolog. c. 37.</hi> and their <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſt.</hi> lib. Expoſ. quar. Propoſ. ad num. 74. <hi>Arnob.</hi> cont. Gentes, lib. 8.</note> reaſons were; <hi>Firſt,</hi> Gods Command binding to obedience, and forbidding reſiſtance, <hi>Rom. 12. 19. Rom. 13. 1, 2. 1 Pet. 3. 13. 18. Secondly,</hi> The ſword is not put into the hands of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, the Prince beareth it, <hi>Rom. 13. 4. Thirdly,</hi> Princes have their Authority from God, and they accounted it unlawfull to rob and deprive them of what God gave them. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Vengeance is threatned againſt them that reſiſt, <hi>Matth. 26. 52. Rom. 13. 2.</hi> Theſe who bear the ſword againſt Rulers (ſaith <hi>Auguſt.)</hi> muſt periſh. <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Chriſtians ſhould be preachers, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſt.</hi> cont. <hi>Fauſt.</hi> l. 2. c. 75 <hi>Cyprian.</hi> ad <hi>Demetr. Auguſt.</hi> Loc. cit. <hi>Arnob.</hi> cont. <hi>Gent.</hi> l. 8.</note> (its <hi>Cyprians</hi> word) of the ſupernaturall vertue of Patience, and not of vengeance. <hi>Sixthly,</hi> By the induring the miſeries of this life, they avouched their hope of a life eternall, ſaith <hi>Auguſt. Seventhly,</hi> That thereby they might make a diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Chriſtian obedience from that of Pagans (ſaith <hi>Anob.)</hi> that whereas theſe yeeld obedience, proceeding only from fear of men, the obedience of Chriſtians ſhould appear to be from conſcience towards God. <hi>Eighthly,</hi> They thought their Faith and Profeſſion glorified by Suffering, which would have been ſtained by reſiſting. <hi>Ninthly,</hi> They knew this was an excellent mean to propagate the Chriſtian Faith; They ſaw that <hi>Sanguis Martyrum</hi> was <hi>ſemen Eccleſiae,</hi> and thereby alſo men were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to ſearch out the evil, for not doing whereof they did ſuffer, and ſo came to know the vanity of Idols, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the good for which they underwent ſo many miſeries, and ſo came to know the excellency of Chriſtian truth. If others ſhould not reſiſt, far leſſe Miniſters who ſhould be Paterns. My tears and Prayers are mine armour (ſaith <hi>Ambroſ.)</hi> for <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amb.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> cont. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and l. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 14. and l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Epiſt. ad <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Bern.</hi> epiſt. 22<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ad <hi>Lodovic.</hi> Regem.</note> ſuch are the defence of Prieſts. We beſeech, O Emperor, we fight not, though all the world ſhould conſpire againſt me (ſaid <hi>Bernard)</hi> to move me to practiſe conſpiracy againſt the Majeſty of the King; I would fear God, and not willingly offend the King ordained of God: for I cannot be ignorant of that which is written, <hi>&amp;c. Rom. 13. 2.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Prerogatives wherewith the great King hath privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged
<pb facs="tcp:34685:6"/> Kings his Lieutenants and Deputies on Earth ſhould work the hearts of Subjects to a ſenſe and practice of their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall duties they owe to Gods Vicegerents, and to an abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency of theſe following ſins. 1. Not to comply with Traytors and Rebels, againſt Gods Anointed, by being a Champion or Leader of them, as <hi>Joab</hi> to <hi>Adonijah;</hi> by being ſpoks-man for them, as <hi>Jeroboam</hi> to his Crue, by blowing the Trumpet, animating them, as <hi>Sheba</hi> to his Crue; by giving them ſhrewd advice how to manage their matters; as <hi>Achitophel</hi> to <hi>Abſolom,</hi> by praying for their ſucceſſe, which was all <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>athar</hi> could do; by harbouring them as the City <hi>Abel</hi> did <hi>Sheba;</hi> by furniſhing them with money, or ſupplies, as the men of <hi>Sechem</hi> to <hi>Abimelech;</hi> by ſpeaking or writing in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Rebels, or their deeds; by praiſing them, calling them the Godly Party, as ſome called <hi>Corah</hi> and his Company the people of the Lord, and Holy: by reviling and curſing, which is the baſe and preſumptuous trade of <hi>Shimei,</hi> of filthy dreamers, and ignorant beaſts, by touching the Kings Perſon, His <hi>Regalia,</hi> His Crown, Authority and Dignity, by wreſting the <hi>Militia</hi> out of His hand, who bears not the ſword in vain, <hi>Rom. 13. 4.</hi> touch theſe once, His perſon will ſoon fall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der contempt, and if they go, His life will not tarry long after.</p>
            <p>As theſe Prerogatives forbid us to meddle with theſe ſins, ſo they call upon us to theſe following duties. 1. To take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice and diſcover Conſpiracies hatched and contrived againſt the Kings Perſon, or Authority, whether by angry <hi>Bigthans</hi> and <hi>Tereſh's,</hi> or crafty <hi>Achitophels,</hi> or fawning <hi>Judaſes.</hi> If <hi>Mordecai</hi> did ſo to an Idolater and oppreſſour of Gods people, what ſhould a Subject do to his lawfull and orthodox Prince. 2. To honour the King, by a reverent conceit of Him, and by an outward honourable teſtimony of the vertues in Him, and the good we receive by Him, <hi>1 Pet. 2. 17. 3.</hi> To pray for them, their perſons and Government, <hi>1 Tim. 2. 2. 4.</hi> To fear them, <hi>Prov. 24. 21. 1 Pet. 2. 18. 5.</hi> To fight for them, not againſt them, <hi>Joh. 18. 36. 6.</hi> To pay them tribute, <hi>Rom. 13. 6, 7.
<pb facs="tcp:34685:6"/> Matth. 17. 27. Matth. 22. 21. 7.</hi> To obey them for conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſake, <hi>1 Pet. 2. 13. 8.</hi> To be thankfull unto God for a good KING, <hi>1 King. 1. 40. 2 King. 11. 12.</hi> and <hi>Pſal. 118.</hi> which was Penned to teach the Subject how to entertain with joy and thankfulneſſe <hi>Davids</hi> advancement to the Throne of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How greatly ſtand we of theſe Nations engaged to God for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtabliſhing among us the beſt of Governments, and ſetling it upon the right ſhoulders, and reſtoring to us our King. It was our ſins which deprived us of Him, becauſe we feared not the Lord, <hi>Hoſ. 10. 13.</hi> and did not thankfully and reverently entertian Him when He was with us, as became dutifull Subjects. The more tyes lyes upon us to bleſſe the Lord, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of our unworthineſſe, yet he hath reſtored Him, and ſet Him upon His Throne with Glory and Honour; and ſo much the rather, in that His Majeſty is no ſtranger by Birth, but our rightfull King; no ſtranger by Religion, not a <hi>Jeroboam</hi> to make the Land ſin, but of that ſame Orthodox Profeſſion with us, and <hi>Fidei defenſor:</hi> Not a <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> not able to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe Himſelf: but a <hi>Solomon,</hi> a <hi>David,</hi> wiſe as an Angel of God to diſcern between good and evil: not a <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> but a <hi>Joſiah</hi> fearing the Lord: not a <hi>Manaſſeh,</hi> but gentle and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull as <hi>David;</hi> not a covetous <hi>Ahab,</hi> but willing rather to diſpenſe with part of His own Revenues. God hath not delt ſo with every Nation, and in this he hath magnified His mercy toward us in giving us ſuch a King, a King <hi>Primae intentionis,</hi> of ſpecial favour. God hath been Schooling us under the rod of Oppreſſors to know the worth of our King, and teach us better principles how to entertain Him with more ſincere, chearfull and conſtant Loyaltie; and I wiſh all may learn their Leſſon well.</p>
            <p>My <hi>Lord,</hi> To teſtifie our thankfulneſſe in this place with publick Narrations, Confeſſions and Praiſes for ſo great and rich a mercy. It was reſolved upon by the <hi>Maſters</hi> and <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> of the Kings <hi>Colledge</hi> here, and Me, to ſet apart a
<pb facs="tcp:34685:7"/> ſolemn day for that gratfull imployment which was ſolemnly gone about by all here, and many others both Miniſters and Profeſſors from ſeveral places of this Countrey, and among others the <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> and many <hi>Inhabitants</hi> of the Honourable and Loyal City of <hi>Aberdeen.</hi> And in this we had the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencie before many of this Nation, that we celebrate here the fourteenth day of <hi>June,</hi> whereas others followed after upon the ninteenth day.</p>
            <p>This Sermon was a part of the work of that day, which when ended, I laid it by, not intending to have ſent it abroad to publick view: But the Maſters of His Majeſties <hi>Colledge</hi> by their often and earneſt entreaties fo far prevailed with me, as to ſend it to the Preſſe: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon which when I had reſolved, then immediately ſome magnetick vertue from your <hi>Lorddſhip,</hi> drew my thoughts towards you, and ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, yet powerfully, engaged me to tranſmit it under your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> Protection. The Sermon it ſelf is plain, in which is nothing but the words of truth and ſobriety; I ſpeak moſt in the words of God; for in preaching, Gods Word ſhould have the preheminence, and therefore I purpoſely forbear to garniſh it with Teſtimonies of humane Writers.</p>
            <p>My <hi>Lord,</hi> When mean men ſpeaks to the King, they do it by the means of ſome <hi>Courtiour,</hi> and when <hi>Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers</hi> ſpeaketh to the Kingdom, they do it under the Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſome worthy Patern. I have made bold to transfer this Sermon to the Nation under your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> Name and Protection: Reaſons moving me were theſe; Firſt, The ſubject of the Sermon is concerning the King; and who ſhould more own and countenance it, then your <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> beloved of the King and advanced by Him to the higheſt place in this Kingdom. Secondly, The eminencie and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catenation of Gods Graces, and Heroick reſplendent Vertues in you, as they have drawn the eyes and hearts of all good and Loyall Subjects, ſo mine too towards your <hi>Lordſhip,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:34685:7"/> and in this I am happy. Wiſdom leadeth men to ſhelter them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their Labours under the wings of the moſt eminent for Piety Learning and Vertue, and ſuch is your <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> by the harmonious teſtimony of truly good men. Thirdly, Your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> good affection manifeſted to honeſt Loyal Miniſters, countenancing and incouraging them, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving them when they came, with chearfulneſſe; inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining them courteouſly, and diſmiſſing them with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment. Fourthly, Your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> zeal for His Majeſties reſtauration, teſtified by your valorous undertaking. When others would not, ye went with a handfull of Loyal Subjects and jeoparded your ſelf in the high places of the Field, and ſo wiſely and valorouſly acquit your ſelf, that ye became a terrour to the Enemy: But when the Lord was not pleaſed to carry on his work by that mean, then your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> teſtified your Loyalty by ſuffering for your Prince. To you it was given, not only to act, but to ſuffer for Him. Fifthly, Tour <hi>Lordſhips</hi> activity and wiſdom in advancing the work of His Majeſties reſtauration when God offered the opportunity, by dealing with the Lord General <hi>Monck,</hi> now Duke of <hi>Albemarlie,</hi> and others of his Army (as I am cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibly informed.) When open acting would have exaſperated enemies, and retarded the Deſigne, ye acted ſecretly and ſucceſſively, for which your praiſe is through the Churches of God in theſe Lands, to the perpetuating your Name to future Ages. Sixthly, Your ſeveral teſtimonies of love and reſpect which your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> was pleaſed to extend to my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Brother Maſter <hi>William Scrougie</hi> Miniſter at <hi>Rathven,</hi> and on ſingular among others, which your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> procured to him from the Kings Majeſty. Be pleaſed therefore moſt Noble <hi>Lord</hi> graciouſly to accept of this my humble addreſſe, and grant me and this Sermon your favourable Protection, for the dayes are evil.</p>
            <p>I have one word more, and ſo I have done, it is my hearts prayer to God, that he will bleſſe His Majeſties Perſon and
<pb facs="tcp:34685:8"/> Government, and make the Crown to flouriſh on His head for many years, and on the heads of His Poſterity, till there be no more time: That He will bleſſe His People with Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, and Obedience; The Miniſters of the Goſpel with zeal for God and the King: The Church of God in this Land, with the continuance both of His precious Truth in Power and Purity, and of the Priviledges and Government thereof: and that He will grant to continue your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> long in the high Charge His Majeſty hath laid moſt worthily upon you, to the Honour of the King, the good of the Commonwealth, the comfort of the Church, the Glory of God, and your own comfort in Him, and that He will perfect His Graces in you, and after many proſperous years on earth, will miniſter an entrance to you into His everlaſting Kingdom. And, I humbly beſeech your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> to conceave of me as I am and ſhall be</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips humbly devoted Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant in all dutifull ſubmiſſion, ALEXANDER SCRO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>GIE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:34685:8"/>
            <head>MIRABILIA DEI.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Pſal. CXXVI. 3.</bibl>
               <q>The Lord hath done great things for us: whereof we are glad.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O ſhow this Text pertiuent to the preſent occaſion, will require no long proceſſe: We may ſay of it, as our Lord Chriſt did of an other Text; <hi>This day is this Scripture ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled in our ears,</hi> Luk. 4. 21. If ever God did great things for theſe Lands and his Church in them, now hath he done them; If ever he gave us cauſe of Rejoycing, ſure this is the time. God did a great work in delivering his People the <hi>Jews</hi> from the <hi>Babylonian</hi> captivity; in freeing their Conſciences from Tyranny, in bringing them home to their own Land, and granting them the free exerciſe of his Worſhip, and in overthrowing their enemies: This was ſo great, that it wrought in the Heathen admiration, and in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves great joy and congratulation. Gods arm is not ſhortned toward us, he hath made it bare and turned again the capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of our Sion, of our King, and advanced him to his Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers, and his own Throne. <hi>He hath put down the mighty from their ſeats, in remembrance of his mercy, and ſcattered the proud in the imagination of their hearts,</hi> Luk. 1. 51, 52. 54. <hi>for
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:34685:9"/> his mercy endureth for ever,</hi> Pſal. 136. 23. and this is ſo great a work, that at firſt it ſeemd incredible to us, ſo great<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that ſtrangers ſtand wondering at it, ſo great, that Enemies ſtands amazed and diſcouraged at it: But I hope it is ſo great in our eyes that it hath wrought, and ere we have done, will work in us a religious Intertainment, a ſolemn and thankfull acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof, and beget in us a great joy, even a full joy, joy of the heart and tongue too, and engage all of us to pray in the higheſt fervency of our ſpirits, for the increaſe and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance thereof.</p>
            <p>To come to the Text; I will firſt ſhew the diverſe readings thereof, and the meaning of the words: The <hi>Arabick</hi> Verſion hath the firſt part of this Verſe, thus, <hi>Multiplicavit Dominus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficium erga nos.</hi> The Syriack, <hi>Multiplicavit Dominus facere nobiſcum.</hi> The <hi>Chaldee</hi> Paraphraſe, <hi>Multiplicavit Dominus benignè facere nobiſcum.</hi> The <hi>Septuagints,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, The Ethiopian, <hi>Magnificavit Dominus facere no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſcum,</hi> ſo the vulgar <hi>Latine: Junius</hi> and <hi>Tremelius, Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca Jehova efficit erga nos:</hi> The laſt words both the <hi>Arabick, Ethiopian</hi> Verſion, <hi>Chaldee</hi> Paraphraſe, and vulgar Latine, reads, <hi>Et facti ſumus laetantes:</hi> the <hi>Syriak, Et facti ſumus in laetitia: Trem.</hi> and <hi>Jun. Sumus laeti:</hi> Auguſt. <hi>Facti ſumus jocundati</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt word in the Original, is <hi>Higdil,</hi> from <hi>Gadal,</hi> which ſignifies to grow or wax great; ſo <hi>Gen.</hi> 26. 23. <hi>the man</hi> (Iſaac) <hi>waxed great:</hi> in <hi>Hiphil,</hi> it ſignifies, to <hi>magnifie,</hi> and alſo to <hi>mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplie,</hi> and ſo here: and it is ſome times taken <hi>intranſitivè,</hi> ſo <hi>Ezek.</hi> 38. 23. <hi>Thus will I magnifie my ſelf,</hi> and other whiles it is taken, <hi>tranſitivè,</hi> ſo <hi>Joſh.</hi> 3. 7 <hi>And the Lord ſaid unto Joſhua, this day will I begin to magnifie thee in the ſight of all Iſrael.</hi> It may be taken both wayes here. Firſt, <hi>Intranſitivè,</hi> I will magnifie my ſelf, to do, or in doing, <hi>efficiendo,</hi> as <hi>Jun.</hi> and <hi>Trem.</hi> in their Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Notes Tranſlate it in the former Verſe, and the Lord did magnifie in this great work: 1. His power, when the people in their bondage were calling for the manifeſtation of his power, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 51. 9. <hi>Awake, awake, put on ſtrength, O arm of the Lord; awake as in the ancient dayes,</hi> &amp;c. It is anſwered in the 11 verſ.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:34685:9"/> 
               <hi>Therefore the redeemed of the Lord ſhall return with ſinging unto Sion, and everlaſting joy ſhall be upon their heads, &amp;c.</hi> and verſ. 14. <hi>The Captive exile haſtneth that he may he louſed, and that he ſhould not die in the pit.</hi> And the reaſon of this is taken from Gods power, verſ. 15. <hi>I am the Lord thy God that divided the ſea whoſe waves roared, the Lord of hoſts is his Name.</hi> and <hi>Nehem.</hi> 1. 10. <hi>Now theſe are thy ſervants whom thou haſt redeemed by thy great power, and by thy ſtrong hand.</hi> 2. His goodneſſe, as it is Jer. 32. 41. <hi>I will rejoyce over them to do them good, and I will plant them in the land aſſuredly with my whole heart, and with my whole ſoul.</hi> And God promiſes to magnifie this his goodneſſe, that it ſhall <hi>be to him a name of praiſe, and an hononr before all the Nations of the earth, which ſhould hear all the good he did to his people,</hi> Jer. 33. 9. 3. His faithfulneſſe, in performing his promiſe: The Lord had promiſed to turn again their captivity, <hi>Jer.</hi> 29. 14. <hi>I will turn away your captivity, and I will gather you from all the Nations, and from all the places whither I have driven you. ſaith the Lord, and I will bring you again to this place.</hi> So Jer. 30. 3. 10. and Chap. 32. 37. 44. and by ſo doing, he magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied <hi>his word</hi> (his gracious promiſe) <hi>above all his Name,</hi> Pſal. 138. 2. 4. His Juſtice, by the overthrow of the <hi>Babylonians,</hi> the enemies of his people, of whom God threatned to take ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 47. 3. by ſending out upon them in a moment, in one day, <hi>Loſſe of Children and Widow-hood</hi> in their perfection: verſ. 9. and <hi>Jer.</hi> 25. 12. he threatned that after ſeventy years were accompliſhed, he would puniſh the King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and that Nation, and make that Land perpetuall deſolations, ſee <hi>Iſa.</hi> 13. and 14. Chap. and <hi>Jer.</hi> 50. and 51. Chap. Secondly, It may be taken <hi>tranſitivè,</hi> and then it relates either to his <hi>facere,</hi> his doing, or to his people; and God did magnifie both, he mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, his doing. For Firſt, he made it appear ſo great and glorious, that the Heathen did notice it, as it is verſ. 3 and <hi>Jer.</hi> 32. he promiſeth that this reſtitution of his people, ſhall be <hi>a name of joy, a praiſe, and an honour before all the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the earth,</hi> and he aſſureth that he will ſo magnifie it, that the Nations ſhall fear and tremble, &amp;c. and it is <hi>Lyra</hi> his obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:34685:10"/> on the place, that Gods doing was ſo magnified in the ſight of the Nations, that thereby ſome of them were turned Proſelyts. Secondly, He magnified his doing, by making it grow and increaſe, as the word in the Original bears, and ye heard ſome Tranſlate it, <hi>multiplicavit:</hi> for this work was not done in a moment, but of a longer tract, being much oppoſed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarded, as appears from <hi>Ezra</hi> and <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> and is clear, by comparing the former Verſes of this <hi>Pſalm</hi> with the prayer in the 4 verſe; but God left not his work in its Infancy, and half done, but ſtill ſtepped on in his glorious working, and multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his work, till the top-ſtone was put on, that all might cry, Grace to the Work, and Glory to the Worker.</p>
            <p>As God did magnifie his doing, and his work, ſo by it he mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified his people: their enemies a little before mockt at their Sabbaths, <hi>Lam.</hi> 1. 7 <hi>They opened their mouths againſt them, they hiſſed and gnaſhed the teeth,</hi> Lam. 2. 16. <hi>Their King, the anointed of the Lord, was taken in their pit,</hi> Lam. 4. 20. <hi>Servants ruled over them,</hi> Lam. 5. 8. Their Prieſts, Elders, Nazarites and Honourable Perſons were filled with contempt, but when God begins to work their reſtauration, he wrought ſo great things, that his people who before were a by-word to curſers, wiſhing theſe they hated, to be dealt with, as the <hi>Jews;</hi> became a patern of bleſſing, ſo that men prayed, theſe they wiſhed beſt unto, might be in the <hi>Jews</hi> caſe, <hi>Zach.</hi> 8. 13. <hi>He made them a name, and praiſe among all the people of the earth, Zephan.</hi> 3. 20. and it is clear from <hi>Ezra</hi> and <hi>Nehem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next word in the Text is, <hi>Lagnaſoth,</hi> from <hi>Gnaſa,</hi> which ſignifieth more then ordinary doing. Criticks obſerve, that in ſtrictneſſe and propriety, the word ſignifies two things: Firſt, to do a thing compleetly and perfectly: Hence <hi>Eſau</hi> had his name, <hi>Gen.</hi> 25. 25. which ſignifieth <hi>Perfect,</hi> becauſe he was full of hair, looking like a grown man with a beard, rather then an Infant without teeth. Secondly, to do exquiſitly, to adorn the work with comlineſſe and beauty, though at firſt their appear diſorder and confuſion in it, yet ere he leave it, and put his laſt hand (as we ſay) to it, to make it appear beautifull; And thus God did
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:34685:10"/> this great work of reſtauration, he made not only an eſſay, and left it in <hi>fieri,</hi> but carried it on to its perfection and beauty too; the work was ſo full of comlineſſe, that it raviſhed beholders unto admiration, and theſe who ſhared in it unto rejoycing and congratulation.</p>
            <p>The third word in the Text is, <hi>Semechim,</hi> from <hi>Samach,</hi> which ſignifieth, not an ordinary, but a great joy, like the joy of the <hi>Harveſt,</hi> and of theſe that divide the <hi>Spoil,</hi> Iſa, 9. 3. and like the joy of a woman when ſhe receiveth a man-childe, <hi>John</hi> 16. 21. The joy of heaven is expreſſed by it, <hi>Pſal,</hi> 16. 11.</p>
            <p>In the words we have two things, Firſt, A ſolemn narration of Gods greatneſſe in working. Secondly, An anſwerable return, by ſolemn rejoycing, or there is Firſt, a worker, <hi>Jehovah,</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, the work and its quality, <hi>done great things.</hi> Thirdly, the appropriating the doing theſe great things <hi>for us.</hi> Fourthly, the Improvement thereof, <hi>whereof we are glad:</hi> Where alſo there is, firſt, the meaſure of that gladneſſe, it was great (as the word imports) in ſome meaſure anſwerable to the work, according to their capacities. Secondly, the ground of it, <hi>Gods great doing for them;</hi> ſo that all in the Text are great, a great worker, the <hi>Lord;</hi> a great work, <hi>great things,</hi> and great joy, the reſult of that work, the great Lord manifeſted his great power by that great work, and the manner of its doing: and the people receive it with anſwerable Intertainment; but in a different way, the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then with great admiration, yet as unconcerned in it; but the <hi>Jews</hi> with great admiration and joy too, as greatly concerned in it: the Heathen acknowledged it, but did not rejoyce in it, and it's like, their acknowledgement was extorted, even by the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thereof: but the <hi>Jews</hi> did both joy in it, and with glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe acknowledge it, and theſe both moſt voluntarly.</p>
            <p>If ye ask what were theſe great things? Anſw. <hi>Great and mighty things,</hi> as the Lord calls them, <hi>Jer.</hi> 33. 3. the breaking the ſnare of the Fowlers, and making his people eſcape, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 124. 7 <hi>Cutting aſunder the cords of the wicked,</hi> Pſal. 129. 4. or as it is in the firſt verſe of this <hi>Pſalm, the turning again their captivity.</hi> Take notice of theſe three great things: 1. God ſtirred up In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:34685:11"/> awakened and lifted them up above themſelves, the chief of whom was <hi>Cyrus</hi> a Heathen King, to whom the Lord having in a ſpecial providencc brought to his notice, the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Propheſies ſpoken 200. years before by <hi>Iſaiah</hi> the Prophet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 44. 28. and 45. 1. 2. did ſo turn his heart towards his people, that he turned away by open Proclamation their Captivity, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 36. 22. and this was a great work, if we conſider, Firſt, That <hi>Cyrus</hi> was a great Monarch, and the <hi>Jews</hi> poor Captives. Secondly, He a Heathen man, and ſtranger to them. Thirdly, He an Idolater, and of himſelf an enemy to their Religion, all theſe ſtood in the way of their deliverance, and might in all likelyhood have turned away his heart from looking after them: but the Lord, the great Commander of hearts, turned his heart to ſend out a Decree for their return, which ſure was a great work.</p>
            <p>The ſecond great thing God did, was the overthrow of the <hi>Babylonians,</hi> who had carried away, and detained <hi>Judah</hi> in cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity, and this was a great work. 1. If we conſider, who, and what they were: The <hi>Babylonian</hi> was one of the greateſt Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates of the world: he made the <hi>earth to tremble,</hi> and ſhook Kingdoms; he made the world as a wilderneſſe, and did not open the houſe of the priſoners, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14. 16, 17. <hi>He ruled the Nations in anger, Iſa.</hi> 14. 6. <hi>All People, Nations, and Languages trembled before him,</hi> Dan. 5. 19. the City was exceeding great and well Fortified, as may be ſeen in <hi>Herodotus,</hi> Lib. 1. and <hi>Plinius</hi> Lib. 6. there were gates of Braſſe, and bars of Iron, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45. and 2. yet notwithſtanding of all theſe, <hi>Babylon</hi> was over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown; and it was the Lord that did it, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45. 1. 2. and this he did for his peoples ſake, <hi>ibid.</hi> verſ. 4.</p>
            <p>The third great work, was the general liberty granted them by Proclamation, to return to their own Land, and this was a great work alſo: for but conſider, Firſt, that their captivity had many great evils in it: 1. They were removed from their own Land given them of the Lord, and <hi>Natale ſolum dulcedine cunctos afficit.</hi> 2. They were robbed of all they had: their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant things given to ſtrangers, their cruel enemies. 3. They were
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:34685:11"/> made bond ſlaves, and that in a ſtrange Land to proud and inſult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing oppreſſors. 4. They were deprived of the free exerciſe of their Religion, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 137. 1, 2, 3. 5. Their ſouls were in capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, for they were threatned to fall down before the great Idol, or elſe be caſt in the fiery furnace, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3. 1. 6. And ſo they were in a worſe caſe in <hi>Babylon,</hi> then in Aegypt: for there, although their bodies were in ſervitude, yet they were not compelled to worſhip the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Idols, <hi>Iſis</hi> and <hi>Oſiris,</hi> now to be delivered from ſuch captivity wherein ſo many great evils were imboſomed, was without doubt a great work of God.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Conſider the manner of their deliverance, and that alſo will ſpeak out the greatneſſe thereof; For, 1. It was ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, they looked not for it. 2. It was free, they bought it not with their money, they purchaſed it not by their ſword; they had no trained Commanders to conduct them to the Fields to fight themſelves into liberty. 3. They did not ſo much as Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for it. 4. In was incredible that a Heathen King, an Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and a ſtranger to them ſhould do it, who would had believed it? eſpecially, it looking to be againſt good Policy to ſet them at liberty, who peradventure might revolt, and breed a new trouble to the State. 5. It was accompanied with much bounty, even all things needfull for their return, as may be ſeen in <hi>Eza,</hi> 1. 4. 7, 8, 9, 10, 11. verſ. 6. It was carried on vigorouſly, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of diſcouragements and dangers of the way, and engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon ſome of the people to ſtay in <hi>Babylon,</hi> they having purchaſed Lands there, and contracted affinity with the <hi>Chaldeans,</hi> and the idleneſſe and laſineſſe of ſome others of them; ſure theſe declare the greatneſſe of that work.</p>
            <p>From the words, I ſhall preſent you ſome Doctrines, with Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication ſuitable to the preſent occaſion: And the firſt I gather by comparing the Text with the former verſe (which I ſhall but name) is, <hi>That it is lawfull to uſe the teſtimony and ſaying of others, although Heathen and Enemies too:</hi> The Heathen ſounded, <hi>The Lord hath done great things for them,</hi> and the <hi>Jews</hi> made the Echo, <hi>The Lord hath done great things for us,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Paul</hi> made uſe of <hi>Aratus,</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Act.</hi> 17. 28. of <hi>Menanders,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 33. of <hi>Epimenides,</hi> Tit. 1. 12.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:34685:12"/> a Heathen; a wicked man may ſometimes let fall a ſavory Truth. <hi>Balaam</hi> and <hi>Cajaphas</hi> may propheſie, and a prophane enemy utter ſome precious Truths which we may repeat, as well as handle Gold that falls from the mouth of Swine: But we muſt take heed; Firſt, that we take up none of their prophane ſayings. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, That when we repeat Truths uttered by them, we do it in an other manner of way: ſure the <hi>Jews</hi> here, though the words were almoſt the ſame, ſpoken by the Heathen, yet they were ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered in an other manner of way as was ſaid before.</p>
            <p>If then, a Papiſt, a Sectary, a Rebell ſay, the Lord hath done great things for us, in turning again our captivity, and reſtoring to us our King, let us not ſtick to ſay it over again, but do it in another manner. Firſt, They ſay it, but it's ſore againſt their wills that ever they had cauſe to ſay it: the greatneſſe of Gods work, hath extorted and wrought it from them, but let us with a willing heart and glad tongue ſay it. Secondly, They utter it, yet can make no right application of it; but let us apply it, for God did not this great work at randome, but for us and our good. Thirdly, They ſay it, but with grief, their hearts are caſt down and diſquieted within them: but let us ſay it with glad hearts, a chearfull countenance, and joyfull lips.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſer.</hi> 2. <hi>The works which God doth in behalf of his diſtreſſed people are great,</hi> he doth great things for them; <hi>it is his property to do great things:</hi> It is true, he doth ſmall things, for the words are not excluſive; He is not like the Heathens <hi>Jupiter,</hi> who took no leaſure to notice ſmall things, nor like <hi>Moſes,</hi> to whom weighty and knotty controverſies were reſerved, and the petty matters tranſmitted and referred to the Inferiour Judges, <hi>Exod.</hi> 18. 26. all things come within the compaſſe of his providence, there is nothing ſo ſmall, but he noticeth it, and his providence hath a hand in it, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10. 29, 30. things that ſeem moſt contingent and caſuall, even to them his providence extendeth; what more caſuall, in reſpect of the means, then when a man ſtriketh to cut down a Tree, and the head of the Axe flees from the helve and ſmites his Neighbour that he die; yet Gods providence hath a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>oak therein, as is clear, by comparing, <hi>Deut.</hi> 19. 5. with
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:34685:12"/> 
               <hi>Exod.</hi> 21. 13. but his glory ſhines moſt in his great doings an works, whether of Juſtice, or mercy; great things he doth in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of his people, to paſſe by the works of Creation, which are great and wondrous, <hi>Job</hi> 9. 10. and of Redemption and Salvation, which are yet far greater; the works of his Providence have among them great ones, the bringing of his people out of <hi>Egypt</hi> through the Red-ſea, and overthrowing <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his Army was a great work, <hi>Exod.</hi> 14. 31. the driving out the <hi>Cananites</hi> before them was a great work, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7. 23. compared with 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 17. 21. and this ſpoken of, in the Text, was a great one, ſo great and ſtrange in the peoples eyes, that it ſeemed in ſome ſort to abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh with them the memoriall of their deliverance out of <hi>Egypt: It ſhall no more be ſaid, the Lord liveth that brought up the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſrael out of the land of Egypt; but the Lord liveth that brought up the children of Iſrael out of the North,</hi> Jer. 16. 14, 15. and <hi>Chap.</hi> 1. 23. 7, 8. when God comes to act for his people, he does like himſelf, his great and glorious power doth great and glorious works, he acteth not like man, who ſometimes take a great deal of pains, and yet doth nothing, or with a great deal of Art and Policy brings forth trifles; but when God comes to viſit his people, we may look for great and noble acts: he is their praiſe and their God that doth for them great and terrible things, <hi>Deut.</hi> 10. 21. and the reaſon hereof is, he is the Lord and not man, a great Lord, and of great power, and will do like himſelf: <hi>Great is our Lord, his underſtanding is infinite: The Lord lifteth up the meek, he caſteth the wicked down to the ground,</hi> Pſal. 147. 5, 6. <hi>He that is mighty doth great things,</hi> Luk. 1. 49. <hi>Thou art great and doſt wondrous things, (O Lord) thou art God alone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What great things God did for his people the <hi>Jews,</hi> ye heard before: But to make Application (which is the work of the day) God hath done for us in theſe Lands not ſmall and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible, but great and glorious acts; I mention five of them. 1. The re-eſtabliſhing of Kingly Government; and to give you a glimpſe of the greatneſſe of this work, conſider firſt the thing it ſelf: Secondly, the evils which followed upon the want of it. Thirdly, the impediments that ſtood in the way of its re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution:
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:34685:13"/> Firſt, view the Government but a little, its the only Government theſe Nations have enjoyed for many hundred years, and this Nation, for neer 2000 years. Secondly, God hath bleſſed theſe Lands under it with many rich bleſſings, both ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and earthly. Thirdly, Its the Government that Scripture doth moſt ſpeak of with approbation, and bleſſed with rare bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings. Fourthly, Its the moſt ancient approved Government amongſt the Nations, as appears from Scripture, and the Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious among the Heathen themſelves: <hi>Certum eſt</hi> (ſayes <hi>Cicero 3. De Legib.) Omnes antiquas gentes regibus p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>imum paruiſſe, principio rerum</hi> (ſaith <hi>Juſtinus,</hi> lib. 1.) <hi>Gentium nationumque Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perium penes reges erat,</hi> and <hi>Callimachus,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ex Jove ſunt Reges.</hi> 2. The miſeris which have of late flowed from and accompanied the want of it, may teach the moſt ſtupid how excellent it is; how many miſeries have we ſeen and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone while we ſtood deprived of it. 1. The Church of God was diſtracted and divided, Schiſmaticall and Erronious perſons countenanced and advanced. 2. The Church it ſelf by ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryed as no Church; her orthodox and venerable Miniſters bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded as Impoſtors. 3. Gods precious Truths detained in unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and Goſpel Truths flooted as Errours. 4. Innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Errours and Hereſies owned and promoted. 5. The privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of Congregations trode upon, and none of the beſt obtrud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon them. 6. The Church Judicatories prohibited, and not yet permitted to ſit, or elſe raiſed by Military force; or if ſuffered to meet, yet forbidden and impeded to act any thing pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiciall to the Intereſt of any perſons although never ſo faulty and Erronious if they did comply with the times and humors o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> theſe in Power. 7. Gods worſhip in ſeveral places interrupted; Miniſters officiating before God abuſed and threatned. 8. All ſin did abound, Rebellion, Murders, Oppreſſion, Cruelty, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erjury, Robery, Uncleanneſſe, Atheiſme, contempt of Gods Ondi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, &amp;c. ſo that it was our caſe, as it was <hi>When there was no King in Iſrael,</hi> Jud. 17. 6. <hi>Every man did that which ſeemed right in hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> own eyes.</hi> 9. Our brethren cut down by the ſword, or car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried captives unto ſtrang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Lands, and ſold for bond-men. 10. Our
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:34685:13"/> Noble-men Diſpiſed, Captivated, Impriſoned, Forefaulted, their Inheritances and Houſes given to ſtrangers, or treacherous and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall Countrey-men. 11. Our Laws lay ſilent, and we made liable to the Arbitrary power of ſtrangers, or men diſaffected. 12. Loyalty was counted a Crime, and Rebellion a Vertue: and ſome came to that height of Atheiſme and Turciſme, as to father their moſt wicked and horrid acts upon God, and <hi>Martion</hi> like derive their Pedegree from him. 13. The Inhabitants of the Land Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veriſhed by Robbery, Ceſſe, and Exciſe, Fines and Compoſitions: To cloſe this in a word, we ſate as a diſconſolate Widow in a dark night lamenting the loſſe of her Husband, her ſolitarineſſe, poverty, and preſſing miſeries: or as a Ship without a Pilot and Helmn, toſſed with tempeſtuous and ſtormy winds and waves among rocks and ſhelves, or purſued by Pirates: or we lay as a beheaded man without breath and life; like a dead Lion over whom every ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous Hare or paltrie abject did inſult at pleaſure without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trole: for our Head the King, <hi>The breath of our noſtrils, the anointed of the Lord, of whom the world was not worthy,</hi> being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the enemies pits, was diſarmed, Impriſoned, and cruelly Murthered, and by that one blow, the three Nations lay Head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, without ſpirit and motion: any breath and motion that ſeemed to be in the bodie, was but like the ſturring of a man new beheaded which ſoon ceaſed; But while we enjoyed that Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in its juſt Priviledges and Authority; we knew not theſe evils: Goſpel Truths did drop as the dew in plenty. Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances were adminiſtred, Church Judicatories were protected, honeſt Miniſters reverenced as the Ambaſſadors of Chriſt, the Laws were in force, Juſtice adminiſtred, Treads and Traffique promot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the Vitious puniſhed, the Vertuous protected and advanced, and propriety ſecured; our Nobles honoured, Rebellion diſcoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced; in a word, it went well with Church and State: Then without peradventure, great is the bleſſing of this Government, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rees us from theſe manifold evils, and brings with it, yea ſecures to us theſe refreſhing and ſolacing mercies; ſo that we may ſay of it, God hath done this great thing for us.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, View the Impediments that ſtood in the way of its
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:34685:14"/> reſtitution. Firſt, When it was brought under ſtrange contempt and oppoſition, was it not ſpoken againſt as unneceſſary and burden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and ſo declared by an Act of their Parliament, and did not ſome perſwade themſelves it to be inconſiſtent with Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity? as if Chriſts Scepter like <hi>Aarons</hi> Rod did ſwallow up the Scepters of earthly Monarchs: But <hi>non eripit terreſtria, qui regna dat coeleſtia.</hi> Did not others like theſe mentioned in <hi>Jude.</hi> 8. and 2 <hi>Pet. 2. 10. Filthy dreamers, preſumptuous, and ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed, diſpiſe dominion, and not afraid to ſpeak evil of dignities,</hi> and thus the bands of Monarchy were looſed and it trode under foot, and its Authority contemned: Yet the Lord, who is won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull in working, wrought ſuch a change, that it is now cryed up as Gods Ordinance, to which all reverence is due, 2 <hi>Pet. 2, 17. Rom. 13. 1. Prov.</hi> 24. 21. He hath made the tongues of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilers, which a little before was their ſhame, now become their glory, to advance its glory by their loud Acclamations. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, When the contempt and oppoſition having the advantage of many years, became ſtrong. To bend a twig is done with little ſtrength, but when it is grown to a ſtrong and confirmed Oak, then either to bend or break it, requires <hi>Samſon-</hi>like ſtrength: The fire when but beginning to ſmoak, is eaſily extinguiſhed; but not ſo, when it comes to a raging flame: To have broken and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed the Anti-monarchicall Party in their raw beginnings, and while they were but Incipients, or ſmall proficients, would have argued no great Power; but when grown to their full height and ſtrength, that to themſelves and others they ſeemed like Gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants inſuperable, when they were habituated in the gain-ſaying of <hi>Corah:</hi> when principles of rebellion, ſeconded with ſucceſſe were habituated, and ſo become an other nature when they were hardened; ſo that the <hi>Ethiopian</hi> could ſooner change his skin, and the <hi>Leopard</hi> his ſpots, then they abandon their Anti-monarchicall principles and practices: Then to overturn them, and reeſtabliſh that which they had pulled down, evidenced and magnified the Lords great power; when the Anarchicall Oak became ſo ſtrong that he defied the Axe, and the ſcales of that Leviathan became ſo hard, that he did laugh at the ſhaking of the Spear, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:34685:14"/> counted Darts as ſtuble; then the great Lord made that great Oak bow as a willow to the tall Cedar of Monarchie, and faſtned his hook in the mouth and ſcales of that Leviathan, ſo that now he is become a ſuppliant, and ſpeaks ſoft words, and hath made a Covenant with Monarchy, to become his ſervant for ever, <hi>Job</hi> 32. 3. The third that ſtood in the way, was the ſeveral luſts of men: As firſt, Diſcontentedneſſe; every bramble being unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with their own condition. 2. Pride and blind ambition, <hi>Abſolon-</hi>like, and <hi>Stanley-</hi>like, in the Reign of <hi>Henry</hi> 7. Some carrying a ſelf King in their boſome, thinking themſelves fitter to Rule, then the Ruler himſelf. 3. Covetouſneſſe the root of all evil, ſetting the Nations on fire, that they might ſteal the goods, and troubling the waters, that they may catch the fiſh; and having catched the prey and booty, became mad againſt Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, leſt it ſhould plume them. 4. Old rooted malice againſt Monarchy upon ſome private and ſelfiſh account, making them reſtleſſe and vigorous in oppoſition. Theſe luſts ſwelling like the raging ſea, upon ſuſpition and hear-ſay of the reſtitution of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, did caſt up mire and dirt, and were enraged at it: But what men could not do to the ſea, the Lord did his power to theſe luſts: <hi>He ſtilled the noiſe of theſe raging waves,</hi> Pſal. 65. and 7. and 69. 9. and tamed their fury, and landed Monarchy ſafe on our Coaſts, and ſet it up amongſt us on its pinacle.</p>
            <p>The ſecond great work, is the ſetting of that Government on the right Shoulders, putting the Crown on the head of Him whoſe by right it is, and ſettling it in the hand of the owner our gracious and dread Soveraign, King <hi>CHARLES</hi> the Second that now Reignes: And this is a great work, if we but conſider theſe. Firſt, the impediments that ſtood in His way. Secondly, ſome things relating to himſelf. I. The impediments, and they were many. 1. The ſins of the Subjects of all rank, ſins againſt His Royal Father, and againſt His Royal ſelf: Here I have a large field; but it is my hearts prayer to God, that he will grant repentance to all, and never charge theſe ſins upon the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders, in the day of their Accounts. Sin is a great obſtructer of mercies, and rendred us unworthy of ſo great a favour as we
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:34685:15"/> now enjoy. <hi>But not for your ſake do I this ſaith the Lord God, be it known unto you: be aſhamed and confounded for your own wayes, O houſe of Iſrael,</hi> Ezek. 36. 32. 2. His Perſon defamed by too many, who made it their work to caſt the ſeeds of prejudice in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hearts of His Subjects, that they ſhould not any more look after Him. 3. Himſelf exiled and impoveriſhed, without Men or Money, the ſinews of War. 4. His Title to the Crown cryed down, and voted down, as if the pooreſt Brat had as good Title to it, as the righteous Heir himſelf. 5. His Poſſeſſions and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues divided among hundreds, to encourage them to withſtand His reſtitution. 6. A victorious Army puft up with Succeſſe, engaged by oath and gain againſt Him. 7. His loyall Subjects rendred uncapable of places of Truſt or Power, Diſarmed, Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veriſhed, Sequeſtrate, Forefaulted, Murdered or Baniſhed, watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed over, as the <hi>Leopard</hi> watches the Traveller, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13. 7. ſo that they were in no capacity to act for Him. 8. A rebellious Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject ſtept up to the Throne, and <hi>Zimri-</hi>like, advanced himſelf by the execrable murder of his Maſter; he catcht that golden Ball, and endeavoured to ſecure it by Power and Policie, and to tranſmit it to his Poſterity, to whom he bequeathed it, but could not leave neither his Brain to manage it, nor Gods bleſſing to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure it: all, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d every one of theſe were high Mountains and deep gulfs to the eye of naturall reaſon, impaſſible gordion knots, not eaſily untwiſted, and Labyrinths inextricable: but the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains are levelled, the Gulfs filled up, and the Knots untwiſted; the Lord who knoweth how to deliver the godly out of temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 9. the only wiſe God hath extricated our King, and by his great power mounted Him upon Eagles wings, <hi>Exod.</hi> 19. 4. over all impediments, and brought Him to us, and His Thrones; and this is ſo great a work that we want words to expreſſe it, or example to paralell it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, View the excellency of our King, behold him in his beauty. I do not take upon me, to draw Him to the life; ye may ſee an imperfect delineation of Him, in others, who will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint you with His Piety, Charity, Mercifulneſſe, Prudence, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety and other Graces and Vertues. I name only ſome things
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:34685:15"/> of Him briefly. 1. He is the right full Heir of theſe Kingdoms. 2. The Son of an incomparable Royal Father, made glorious not only by His Piety. Equity, Clemency, but alſo by His Sufferings and Patience under the croſſe, and love towards all His Subjects, and Charity towards His Implacable Enemies, and by Martyrdom it ſelf. 3. If the general approbation which he hath among Princes and People abroad, even theſe of a different perſwaſion, but eſpecially, the high eſteem He hath among the Proteſtant Churches abroad, can add any weight to His Glory, He wants not this: His praiſe is throughout all the Churches, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 18. 4. God who knows to put a right eſtimate upon every perſon and thing, hath highly and conſpicuouſly made known to all, how ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent He is in His ſight, by His ſpecial care of Him, and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull preſerving of Him from ſo many and great dangers: for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing to ſpeak of all, look but to His dangers at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> where His horſe was twiſe ſhot under Him; His Army over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powered with multitudes, routed; Himſelf hotly purſued by His Enemies, but not overtaken, being neceſſitated to diſ-robe Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of His Princly Ornaments, and cut His hair, and forced with one Servant to wander unto a Wood, and there to make an hollow Oak His Caſtle of refuge; yet not found out, although ſearched after: thereafter rides thro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gh a Troup of His Enemies, yet not diſcovered: at an other time by providence in company with one of His notorious Enemies, yet not noticed; a great ſum of money ſet on His Head, and offered to any that would diſcover or apprehend him; for which many out of covetouſneſſe made it their buſineſſe to ſearch for Him; all places of eſcape watched; yet ſo wonderfull were the ſteps and hand of Gods Fatherly Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence going along with Him, that He gets ſafe into a Forraign Countrey: while He is abroad, He is not ſuffered to live at quiet, but is ſtill in danger of Powder plots, poyſoning and otherwiſe. <hi>Achitophels</hi> contrived His ruine; <hi>Nabals</hi> refuſed Him Intertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; ſome of His familiar Friends lift up the heel againſt Him, ſo that He might have ſaid, as once <hi>Tyberius, Timeo incuſtoditos aditus, timeo ipſos cuſtodes:</hi> I fear the paſſages that are not kept, I fear them who are ſet to be keepers, or as <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 16, 17.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:34685:16"/> 
               <hi>No man ſtood with me, all men for ſook me—notwithſtanding, the Lord ſtood with me—and I was delivered out of the mouth of the Lion: The Lord numbered the hairs of his head,</hi> Matth. 10. 30. <hi>Gave his Angels charge over him,</hi> Pſal. 91. 1. <hi>His enemies con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived miſchief, but brought forth a lie,</hi> Pſal. 7. 14. <hi>He that neither ſlumbers nor ſleeps, was his keeper, and preſerved his going out, and coming in,</hi> Pſal. 121. 5. 8. <hi>and made him glorious by ſalvation,</hi> Pſal. 21. 6. 5. His Majeſties conſtant adhering to the Proteſtant Truth (notwithſtanding the many and ſtrong tentations to alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate His heart therefrom) ſpeaks out His admirable excellency: Look but upon theſe five tentations. Firſt, How ill was He uſed and entertained by ſome of His own Subjects in Power, highly pretending the Truths preſervation, being by them defamed, exiled, impoveriſhed and perſecuted, and by too many others forſaken. Secondly, A note of ignominie caſt upon the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion by theſe of the contrare perſwaſion, or Atheiſticall ignorants, as if it were a principle of our Religion to rebell and dethrone our own Kings (which wrought ſo powerfully upon ſome unſtable ſouls, as to lead them to a deteſtation of the truth and wayes of God,) where as true Proteſtants teach no ſuch ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and treaſonable Doctrine, but does abhor it as the Doctrine of Divels, taught by Jeſuites, Anabaptiſts and other Sectaries, and with all our hearts, and with deepeſt deteſtation condemneth that execrable murder of our late King. Thirdly, He was hotly aſſaulted and ſolicited by ſome Champions of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, and eſpecially by ſome who had Apoſtatized from the Truth them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and ſo knew the better how to perſwade others. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, He receives kind intertainment and protection from ſome of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Party. Fifthly, Aſſiſtance was offered by them of that perſwaſion unto Him, if He would turn Papiſt; were not all theſe ſtrong tentations? yet His heart was indivertible from God and His Truth, that neither ill uſage from His own, nor fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours conferred and offered by ſtrangers could work that change, His heart like <hi>Davids was fixed, truſting in the Lord, his heart was eſtabliſhed,</hi> Pſal. 112. 7, 8. <hi>He hid Gods word in his heart, that he ſhould not ſin againſt him,</hi> Pſal. 119. 11. and this was a great and ſpecial work of the Lords.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:34685:16"/>
            <p>The third great work God hath done for us, is, the bringing again our captivity; of which remark but theſe ſhortly. Firſt, It was Nationall, for although we were not all exiled, yet we were captivated in our own Land, like a man Impriſoned in his own Houſe; and this was a ſore ill. A generous Woman once ſaid, <hi>Mallem mille mortes quam tributaria capita circumferre.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, It was of a large extent, reaching to all ranks. Our King exiled, our Nobles Impriſoned, many of our brethren car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away, further then from <hi>Judea</hi> to <hi>Babylon,</hi> even to <hi>Barbado's,</hi> and ſome of the Miniſters of Chriſt removed from their own Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Flocks. Thirdly, Our captivity was ſpirituall, to ſin, impoſed on us by threatning, as was done to the <hi>Jews</hi> in <hi>Babylon.</hi> We wer threatned and urged to ſubſcribe their <hi>Tender,</hi> thereby to diſclaim our King and the ancient Government of theſe Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and to bow to there <hi>Idol</hi> of Anarchie and Uſurpation, to which too many readily yeelded: Miniſters were prohibited, upon no leſſe pain, then ſilencing them from preaching the Goſpel to pray for His Majeſty, a duty that lay upon all by Gods reiterated Commands. All commanded to keep dayes of Thankſgiving for diſcovery of plots againſt Uſurpers, which was a juſtifying of them in their wicked Uſurpations, and proclaiming to the world, that God was well pleaſed with them and their wayes. Fourthly, It reached even to the Church, and Truth of God, the Government thereof decreed as Antichriſtian, her Diſcipline oppoſed and ſlighted; Religion hazarded by a vaſt Act of Toleration, her Miniſters flouted, and while they were officiating before God, abuſed, her Worſhip interrupted, her Patrimony ſeaſed upon, ſome crying out, <hi>Let us take to our ſelves the Houſes of God in poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> Pſal. 83. 12. her Judicatories interrupted, and Gods Servants driven out from the General Aſſemblies and made ſpecticles to men and Angels; but the Lord hath turned away this our cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity, and it is his great and glorious doing.</p>
            <p>The fourth great work, was the overthrow of the Kings and our Enemies: 1. They were many. 2. Proud, puft up with Succeſſe. 3. Deſperate, whom no command of the Lord could bow, nor threatning affright. 4. Cruel, acted by Jeſuiticall and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:34685:17"/> Anabaptiſticall Furies. 5. Covetous, being mad upon unjuſt gain, and als mad in the retention of it. 6. United and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bined together by all the ligaments of carnall Policy: Yet the great and good Lord divided them, and they melted away like a ſnail, he laid their pride in the duſt, and turned theſe boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Lamechs</hi> into Cowards, and made them flee as chaffe before the wind; ſo that we may apply that ſaying of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 76, 5. <hi>The ſtout hearted are ſpoiled, and none of the men of might have found their hands.</hi> At the appearance of that chief Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they cryed out as the <hi>Egyptians</hi> of old, <hi>Exod.</hi> 15. 25. <hi>Let <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s flee from the face of Iſrael for the Lord fighteth for them againſt the Egyptians,</hi> and this was the Lords great doing.</p>
            <p>The fifth great work is, the raiſing up Inſtruments for carrying on theſe great Works: I name but ſix. 1. The Lord Generall <hi>George Monck,</hi> an other <hi>Cyrus</hi> to us, who wrought under God the foreſaid great things: He our <hi>Ezra</hi> or help, our <hi>Nehemiah</hi> or Comforter, our <hi>Zerubbabel,</hi> or mighty One, made ſo by the mighty God of Britain: before whom the great Mountains be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a plain, <hi>Zecha.</hi> 4. 7. and <hi>Huſhai-</hi>like defeated the crafty counſels of <hi>Achitophels:</hi> 2. His <hi>Debora,</hi> whoſe loyal heart made her put forth the uttermoſt of her conjugall influence. 3. The good and loyal people of <hi>England,</hi> influenced by the breathings of the Spirit of the Lord, calling for a free Parliament, and their and our King. 4. The right Honourable, the City of <hi>London,</hi> joyning their endeavours with the Lord General and People of the Land. 5. That famous Parliament that now ſits, crowning the work by their unanimous calling home His Majeſty, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring Him to His juſt Priviledges and Authority. 6. The Lord General <hi>Montague</hi> who proved active to engage the Navie to own His Majeſty, and waft Him over ſafe unto His own Kingdoms. That ſo many ſhould all with one mouth and hand carry on ſo great a work is unto me an argument of Gods approving and working thereof: for as it is an argument of the Divine Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the propheticall Scriptures, that the Prophets though they lived in divers places and ages of the World, yet they all agreed in one and the ſame Truth, as if they had all ſpoken by
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:34685:17"/> one and the ſame mouth, as ye have it, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1. 70. <hi>As He ſpake by the mouth</hi> (not mouths) <hi>of His holy Prophets.</hi> So when God ſtirreth up his Servants in all places of the Kingdom, and them of all ranks, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>etteth them all about one work, as if they were one man, it may be taken for no leſſe then Gods doing; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if ye conſider the caſe of our King, while they begin to act for Him; not ſitting on His Throne and ſwaying the Scepter, but in His low eſtate, even then to remember Him, and lay themſelves out for Him; ſpeaks out Gods great doing, and that not only His finger, but His whole hand, yea His ten fingers, yea both His arms (to ſpeak after the manner of man) was lifting up theſe Inſtruments and imploying them in His work, and to this we may add; that theſe Inſtruments ſhould undertake the work againſt ſo many high and great Mountains that ſtood in the way; againſt ſo many ſons of <hi>Anak,</hi> and mighty Gyants combined ſo ſtrongly together, and yet levell them all, and ſcatter them all, can ſpeak no leſſe then that the mighty Spirit of God was in them, and His ſtrong hand with them.</p>
            <p>Take a word more to advance the greatneſſe of all theſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and works, and for that end conſider, Firſt, The time when; When we like the <hi>Jews</hi> thought it Impoſſible, at leaſt ſo ſoon, we were like theſe <hi>dry bones,</hi> Ezek. 37. our hope was almoſt loſt, <hi>verſ.</hi> 11. yet though it ſeemed difficult in our eyes, it was not ſo in Gods, <hi>Zech.</hi> 8. 6. to whom all things are poſſible, <hi>Matth.</hi> 19. 26. and doth whatſoever he will, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 135. 6. he breathed upon us, and by his great doing hath made us live and ſtand up in his fight, both our King and us his People, and delivered Him and us from the hand of our enemies, and bleſſed us as in the dayes of old.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Conſider the manner; it was without blood or ſore labour: <hi>Jud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h</hi> was not ſo delivered, but God hath magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied his doing toward us; for our enemies melted away as a ſnail which melteth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 58. 8. <hi>As ſmoak is driven away</hi> ſo were they, as <hi>wax melteth before the fire, ſo did they periſh at the preſence of God,</hi> Pſal. 68. 2.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Conſider by whom, and in this alſo God hath magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied his great doing: it was not the <hi>Babylonians,</hi> but <hi>Cyrus</hi> that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:34685:18"/> ſet the <hi>Jews</hi> at liberty; but here, many of theſe who were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentall againſt the King, are now under God, the means of His reſtitution. The great God who changed <hi>Labans</hi> heart to enter in Covenant with <hi>Jacob,</hi> Gen. 31. 34. and made theſe who joyned with <hi>Abſolon</hi> in his rebellion againſt <hi>David</hi> their King, prove afterwards moſt forward to call him home, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19. 9. he bowed alſo their hearts to ſhow all forwardneſſe for our Kings reduction, and kiſſe Him with the kiſſes of ſubjection and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and will, we hope ere long, ſecure them to Him by the Oath of Allegiance: As <hi>the hearts of Kings are in the hand of the Lord, and he turneth them whether ſoever he will,</hi> Prov. 21. 1. ſo are the hearts of Armies and Subjects in his hands, and he hath turned them by his mighty influence to run in the ancient and right channell, as we ſee this day.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. Let us improve the Doctrine: And firſt, let no proud oppreſſing Tyrant glory in his might, and boaſt like <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> Exod. 5. 2. <hi>Who is the Lord, that I ſhould obey his voice, to let Iſrael go? I know not the Lord, neither will I let Iſrael go:</hi> or as <hi>Senacherib, Can God deliver out of my hand,</hi> 2 Chron 32. 14, 15. preſumptuous fools, the fooliſhneſſe of God is wiſer then men, and the weakneſſe of God is ſtronger then men, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 25. He bindeth the arms of the ſtrongeſt, and taketh the prey from the mighty, he catcheth the wiſeſt in their own wiles, <hi>He break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the bow, and cutteth the ſpear in ſunder,</hi> Pſal. 46. 9. <hi>He bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth out thoſe which are bound with chains,</hi> Pſal. 68. 6. <hi>He woundeth the head of his enemies,</hi> verſe 21. <hi>and brings his people from the depths of the ſea,</hi> verſe 22. No might nor policie can withſtand Him, <hi>Mountains melt at his preſence.</hi> When he writes, <hi>Mene Tekel</hi> on the wall, the ſpirit of the mighty fails, their thoughts are troubled, their countenance changed, their joynts looſed, their knees ſmite one againſt another, and the Tyrant is forced to cry out, <hi>Do victas in tua vincla manus,</hi> and with <hi>Julian, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſti tandem Galilaee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. Secondly, Fear the great Lord greatly, who can do great things both for us and againſt us: this uſe the Pſalmiſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89. 6. <hi>Who in heaven</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>can be compared
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:34685:18"/> to the Lord? Who among the ſons of the mighty can be likned unto to Lord:</hi> and then from this he in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erreth, <hi>verſe</hi> 7. <hi>God is greatly to be feared in the Aſſembly of the Saints,</hi> and Exod. 14. 31. <hi>Iſrael ſaw that great work which the Lord did upon the Egyptians; and the people feared the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 3. Thirdly, Expect great things from him who can do them; we diſhonour him when we expect only little and but ſmall things, as he requireth our greateſt ſervices, becauſe he is a great Father and a great Maſter, even the Lord of hoſts, <hi>Mal.</hi> 1. 6. ſo it becomes us to expect from him great things, becauſe he is a great King, that worketh wonders: how unbeſeeming is a pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie fidian and a great God; a little ſaith and a great Lord, doing great things?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 4 Fourthly, Let none in the deepeſt diſtreſſe diſpaire of his own, or of the deliverance of Gods people, although it ſeem incredible and above the reach of mans reaſon and power, although thy condition ſeem deſperate in the eyes of the enemie, that he ſay, <hi>God hath forſaken thee, there is none to deliver thee, Pſal.</hi> 71. 11. although it ſeem ſo unto thy neighbours and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance that they look upon thee as a dead man out of mind; and like a broken veſſel, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31. 12. and although it ſeem ſo in thine own eyes, that thou ſay, as it is in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37. 12. <hi>Our bones are dried, and our hope is loſt, we are cut off for our parts:</hi> yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, <hi>The Lord knoweth how to deliver the godly out of tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and to reſerve the unjuſt unto the day of Judgement to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed,</hi> 2 Pet. 2. 9. Fear ye not, (as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid to the people) <hi>Stand ſtill and ſee the ſalvation of the Lord which he will ſhew you,</hi> Exod. 14. 13. <hi>Believe in God who quickneth the dead, and calleth theſe things which be not, as though they were,</hi> Rom. 4. 17. <hi>Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that unto God belongeth the iſſues from death,</hi> Pſal. 68. 20. <hi>and that to him all things are poſſible,</hi> Matth. 19. 26. and improve the former experiments of Gods great doings in behalf of his people, or of thy ſelf, to the ſtrengthning of thy faith in after times. Conclude from former experience to future, ſo did <hi>David,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17. 31. and ſo did <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 10. as former Victories encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage Conquerors to a new Conqueſt: ſo old deliverances and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:34685:19"/> ſhould help us ſtill to truſt in God, and ſtand nudaunted in all our troubles. Let us therefore regiſter Gods former favours, and the great things he hath done for us, and make them as many Arguments to build upon God for time to come; for God is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes where he was the ſame without any ſhaddow of change.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 5. Fifthty, Give God great praiſe for his great doings; he will accept no lean or ſtarved ſacrifices; <hi>Great is the Lord, and greatly to be praiſed,</hi> Pſal. 48. 1. and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145. 3. When the Lord did a great work for <hi>Paul,</hi> in delivering him from the Lions mouth, he breaketh forth into great praiſe, to him be glory for ever and ever amen, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 18. when the Lord turned again the captivity of his people, their tongue was filled with ſinging the ſongs of praiſe, as it is, verſe 2. God hath turned again our Kings and our captivity, for ours was bound up in His: Let us for this great work, render unto God great and ample praiſe, this is the end of all Gods doings (for he doth all for his own glory) and let this be our end to give the praiſe of all to him, even praiſe in ſome meaſure anſwerable to his doing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſ.</hi> 2. Secondly, we obſerve <hi>Gods prerogative,</hi> what ever great things are done for his people, he is the doer of them, he is the ſole Author of his peoples good, whether of their deliverance, or their enjoyment of good things, or the overthrow of their enemies; He is the Author alſo of their miſery, <hi>Amos</hi> 3. 6. and <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45. 7. God fits not as an idle ſpectator, and leaves fortune to tumble things up and down, but he is otherwayes the Author of good then of evil, he is provocked by man to afflict; <hi>For he doth it not willingly,</hi> Lam. 3. 33. He is in a manner inforced to it by mans ſins, and therefore, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28. it is called his <hi>Work,</hi> but <hi>his ſtrange work,</hi> his Act, but his <hi>ſtrange Act,</hi> but of his peoples good; He is <hi>cauſa</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, he is the Author and occaſion: it comes of himſelf: he moved only by his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, doth great things for them, this ſame work of the peoples deliverance, is thriſe aſcribed to God, in this Pſal. verſe 1, 2, 3. and God himſelf told his people, that he would be the doer of it, <hi>Jer.</hi> 30. 8, 9, 10. Though he made uſe of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> yet God was the principle, and <hi>Cyrus</hi> but his Inſtrument; <hi>He ſtirred up his ſpirit,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:34685:19"/> and held his right hand to ſubdue nations before him.</hi> Iſa. 45. 1. and therefore he ſubjoyns there, verſe 5. <hi>I am the Lord and there is none elſe: I girded thee, though thou haſt not known me. He is the Lord, and beſide him there is no Saviour,</hi> Iſa. 43. 11. <hi>He alone doth great wonders,</hi> Pſal. 136. 4. <hi>Salvation is of the Lord alone,</hi> Jonah 2. 9.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Applic.</hi> To make Application. Though the Army was Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall in His Majeſties reſtauration; and though the Lord Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall did his utmoſt to perſwade them to that great undertaking; yet if the Lord had not moved their hearts, they had not moved their hearts, they had not moved nor promoved the Work. There went with King <hi>Saul</hi> a band of men, but God firſt touched their hearts, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10. 26. elſe they had proved as ill as others, children of Belial, and deſpiſed him, as it is there, <hi>verſe</hi> 27. King <hi>Saul</hi> ſent a ſevere Edict, requiring the Subjects to give their aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance for the relief of <hi>Jabeſ-gilead:</hi> but it was not the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>everity of the Proclamation that brought them to obedience, but when the fear of the Lord fell on them, <hi>Then they came with one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,</hi> 1 Sam. 11. 7. There is no Saviour beſide him, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 13. 4. It was the Lord who did begin and carried on this work which we commemorate this day: Its beginning, progreſſe, and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment is all of him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. Then firſt, Let no Inſtrument miſtake himſelf, for the authour, nor advance himſelf above his ſphear, nor appropriate to himſelf the Lords prerogative: It was the folly of the proud <hi>Babylonians</hi> to do ſo, <hi>Hab.</hi> 1. 16. <hi>They ſacrificed to their own net, and burned incenſe unto their drag;</hi> The <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> alſo was deeply guilty of this, as you have it, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10. 13. What God had done by him as an Inſtrument, he arrogates to himſelf, and aſcribes to his own power and policie. Inſtruments are ſometimes ready with <hi>Iſrael</hi> to glory in their ſtrength and ſucceſſe, which is but a thing of nought, and ſay, <hi>That they have taken horns to themſelf by their own ſtrength,</hi> Amos 6. 13. but Inſtruments ſhould not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>acrilegiouſly robe God of his honour nor Dèifie themſelves. Let them beware leſt their hearts be lifted up and forget the Lord who hath done great things by them, and ſay in their heart,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:34685:20"/> their power and might of their hand, their policie and induſtry hath done theſe things, ſee <hi>Deut.</hi> 8. 14. 17.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. Secondly, Let Inſtruments then be exhorted in a ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denying way, to ſay, <hi>Not unto us, not unto us, O Lord, but unto thy Name, give glory,</hi> Pſal. 115. 1. and with <hi>Paul</hi> in an other caſe, 1 Cor. 15. 10. <hi>By the grace of God, I am what I am, and his grace which was beſtowed upon me, was not in vain, I laboured abundantly, yet not I but the grace of God which was with me, for they prevailed not by their ſword, nor did their right arm ſave them, but the right hand of the Lord, and his arm, and the light of his countenance, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he favoured them,</hi> Pſal. 44. 3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 3. Thirdly, My exhortation from this is to others: Firſt, that they Idolize no Inſtrument. When the people upon the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Herods</hi> Oration gave a ſhout, <hi>And cried, it is the voice of a God, and not of a man;</hi> this puft him ſo up with pride, that he gave not glory to God, and therefore it turned to his ruine, <hi>Act.</hi> 12. 21. 22, 23. Two extreams there would be ſhunned The firſt is: not to Deiefie Inſtruments, although never ſo great, ſet them not up in Gods room, for God will not give his glory to another <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42. 8. and as ſalvation is in vain expected from them, truly (ſaith the Prophet) <hi>In vain is ſalvation hoped for from the hills and from the multitude of mountains, truly in the Lord our God is the ſalvation of Iſrael,</hi> Jer. 3. 23. ſo it is impiouſly aſcrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them: for what could they have done without God, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out whom they can do nothing, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15. 6. God it is who work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth by them what he pleaſeth. God ſaid of <hi>Cyrus</hi> his Inſtrument, <hi>Thou art my ſhepherd and ſhall perform all my pleaſure,</hi> Iſa. 44. 28. The other extream to be avoided, is the neglect of Inſtruments; Idolize them we may not, forget them we ſhould not; remember them with civill honour and praiſe we ought: are not <hi>Moſes, Joſhua,</hi> the ſeveral Judges, <hi>Deborah, David, Cyrus,</hi> and other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of the Lord for his peoples good recorded in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with honour; in the 5 of <hi>Judges, Deborah</hi> remembereth with honourable reſpect theſe who helped againſt the enemy, others are branded with a note of Infamy, for withholding their aſſiſtance, and <hi>Meroz</hi> is curſed with a grievous curſe, becauſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:34685:20"/> being neer and called to give their aſſiſtance, they refuſed to do it, and 23. let us then remember the Inſtruments before named with civil reſpect and praiſe. Should we not honour them whom the Lord hath honoured; let them be Chronicled to ſucceeding Generations; <hi>my heart is towards them:</hi> (To uſe <hi>Deborah</hi> her wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Judg.</hi> 5. 9.) <hi>That offered themſelves willingly, bleſſe the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 4. Fourthly, Give all the Divine praiſe to God; praiſe him in and for himſelf; he is the principall and author of theſe great works, <hi>For of him, and through him, and to him are all things, to whom be glory for ever, Amen,</hi> Rom. 11. 36. When <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> was delivered from his enemies he gave the praiſe of all to the Lord, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 27, 28. ſo did <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> being certified of the overthrow of <hi>John</hi> the Uſurper, <hi>Socrat.</hi> lib. 7. cap. 23. ſo did the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> when <hi>David</hi> their King was advanced to his Throne, ſee <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118. It is true, we cannot ſufficiently utter the mighty acts of the Lord, nor ſhew forth all his praiſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106. 2. yet according to our capacity, let us ſing with <hi>Moſes; The Lord is my ſtrength and ſong, he is become my ſalvation.—The Lord is a man of war,—Thy right hand, O Lord, is become glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in power,—who is like unto thee, O Lord, among the gods: Who is like thee glorious in holineſſe, fearfull in praiſes, doing won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> Exod. 15. 2, 3. 11. Let the King ſay with <hi>David, It is God that avaingeth me, and ſubdueth the people under me; he deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth me from mine enemies: yea, thou lifteſt me up above theſe that riſe up againſt me; thou haſt delivered me from the violent man, therefore will I give thanks unto thee, O Lord, and ſing praiſes unto thy name. Great deliverance giveth he unto his King, and ſheweth mercy to his Anointed, &amp;c.</hi> Pſal. 18. 47, 48, 49, 50. Let all of us ſay, <hi>O Give thanks unto the Lord, for his mercy endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth for ever; to him who alone doth great wonders, for his mercy endureth for ever,</hi> Pſal. 136. 3, 4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 5. Fifthly, Rely upon God alone in time of trouble, for he alone doth great things for his people; <hi>It is better to truſt in the Lord, then to put confidence in man,—then to put confidence in Princes,</hi> Pſal. 118. 8, 9. <hi>Put not your truſt in Princes, nor in the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:34685:21"/> ſon of man in whom there is no help,</hi> Pſal. 146. 3. Yea, the Lord curſeth him that truſteth in man, <hi>that maketh fleſh his arm, and whoſe heart departeth from the Lord.</hi> Make not wealth our ſtrong City, as the rich do, <hi>Prov.</hi> 18. 11. for neither ſilver nor gold ſhall be able to deliver in the day of the Lords wrath, <hi>Prov.</hi> 11. 4. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 7. 19. <hi>Zeph.</hi> 1. 18. But let the Lord be our City of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>fuge and ſtrong Tower: run unto him, <hi>for he ſees our affliction and hears our cry,</hi> Exod. 3. 7. 1 Pet. 3. 12. and <hi>He will ſave us,</hi> Pſal. 18. 3. Prov. 18. 10. <hi>for ſalvation is of him,</hi> Jonah 2. 9.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſ.</hi> 3. Thirdly, <hi>Gods great doing ſhould be well noticed:</hi> the Heathen did it, verſ. 2. and his people in the Text. <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> with the men, and <hi>Miriam</hi> with the women of <hi>Iſrael</hi> took notice of their deliverance from the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> Exod. 15. 1. 20. <hi>David</hi> was very carefull to remark Gods diſpenſations, and pens many a Pſalm on that account. <hi>Debora</hi> and <hi>Barak</hi> ſo noticed the deliverance of Gods people from <hi>Jabin</hi> and <hi>Siſera,</hi> that they commemorate it with ſongs of praiſe, <hi>Judg.</hi> 5. When the men of <hi>Judah</hi> got their young King <hi>Joaſh</hi> reſtored to the Crown beyond expectation, they obſerved it, with clapping their hands and prayer for him, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 11. 12. And when <hi>Athalia</hi> the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant was ſlain, all the people of the Land rejoyced, verſe 20. the Lord commands his people to notice his doings, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 46 8. <hi>Come and ſee,</hi> (ſaith the Pſalmiſt) <hi>the works of God,</hi> Pſal. 66. 4. the nature of his works call for it, being great, honourable, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and wonderfull, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 111. 2, 3, 4. The godly takes plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to ſeek them out, <hi>Ibid.</hi> verſe 2. God ſheweth his people the power of his works, verſe 6. that they may notice them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. <hi>Come then, and behold, what the Lord d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th done for us,</hi> Pſal. 46. 8. take reaſons to move you. 1. Ye offer a great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignity to God the doer, if ye remark them not. When a great Crafts-man hath brought a great and rare peice of Work to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and calls on us to look upon it, if we refuſe, do we not affront him? The Lord will ſure take it as a high con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, if we do not conſider his workings. 2. His doings and workings are ſo full of raviſhing wiſdom, power and love, that there is in them a magnetick vertue to draw out our con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>idera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:34685:21"/> and meditation, and make us cry out as of all Gods works, ſo of theſe in particular, <hi>There are no works like unto thy works,</hi> Pſal. 86. 8. Who is like unto thee, O <hi>Brittain, O people ſaved by the Lord,</hi> Deut. 33. 29. <hi>Ask now of the dayes that are paſt—and and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k from one ſide of the heaven unto the other, whether there hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>en any ſuch things as theſe great things are,</hi> Deut. 4. 32. <hi>Who hath heard, or ſeen ſuch things? Shall the earth be made to bring forth in one day, or ſhall a Nation be born at once?</hi> Iſa 66. 8. but ſudainly, ſo ſmoothly, ſo wiſely, ſo gloriouſly hath the Lord done theſe great things for us. 3. Theſe things are done in our ſight. God did marveilous things in the ſight of his people in <hi>Egypt, in Zoan,</hi> Pſal, 78. 12. he hath done them in our ſight, that we with open face might behold them. 4. Strangers noticeth them, they are ſaying as the Heathen did, verſe 2. and crying, <hi>This is the finger of God,</hi> Exod. 8. 19. and ſhall we not with the people in the Text, Echo them, and recog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize his doing. 5. It is a ſigne of a wicked man, that <hi>when Gods hand is lifted up, he will not ſee,</hi> Iſa. 26. 11. Notice then Gods do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, but do it, Firſt, adviſedly, not ſlightly: Men <hi>ſhould wiſely conſider of his doings,</hi> Pſal. 64. 9. <hi>Stand ſtill and ſee this great ſight,</hi> Exod. 3. 3. <hi>Who is wiſe and will obſerve theſe things, even they ſhall underſtand the loving kindneſſe of the Lord,</hi> Pſal. 107. 43. Secondly, With joy and delight: The righteous ſhould ſee and rejoyce, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107, 42. for God doth his works to make his people glad, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 92. 4. Thirdly, Believingly and profitably, to the ſtrengthning our Fath and Hope for times to come, that we may ſet our hope in God and keep his Commandments <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78. 7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. Then juſtly reprovable are three ſorts of men who come ſhort of this duty, in noticing Gods doings. Firſt, care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and ignorant ones, who like Swine take no notice of theſe Pearles, <hi>How great are thy works, O Lord—a brutiſh man know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not, neither doth a fool underſtand this,</hi> Pſal. 92. 5, 6. ſome are like the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> of whom it is ſaid, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106. 7. that they underſtood not Gods wonders, in <hi>Egypt;</hi> but theſe provocketh God, as it is in that ſame verſe. Secondly, Deſpiſers, who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervalue his doings: <hi>They regard not the works of the Lord nor
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:34685:22"/> the operation of his hands,</hi> Pſal. 28 5. Iſa. 5. 12. like Swine, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferreth the Accorn to the Pearl, or children in knowledge, triffles to Gold: to ſuch may be ſaid, as it is, <hi>Act.</hi> 13. 41. <hi>Behold ye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſers, and wonder and periſh:</hi> God will deſtroy ſuch, and not build them up, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 28. 5. Thirdly, Envious perſons, who envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the glory of our King, and the happineſſe of theſe Lands; of ſuch the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeaketh, chap. 26. 11. <hi>But they ſhall ſee, and be aſhamed, for their envie,</hi> &amp;c. for their envious and ſpight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full carriage towards God's people, they ſhall be aſhamed and confounded.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſ.</hi> 4. Fourthly, <hi>Gods great works ſhould be publickly acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged:</hi> not only noticed, but acknowledged, noticed with ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Narrations and Commemorations: ſo did <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> notice and commemorate with publique con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions and praiſes. <hi>Debora,</hi> Jud. 5. is large in acknowledging Gods great doings. It is commanded that we declare among the people his doings, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9. 11. and <hi>David</hi> engageth to do it, in that <hi>Pſalm,</hi> verſe 1. <hi>I will ſhew forth,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>all thy marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous works,</hi> and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 26. 6, 7. <hi>I will compaſſe thine altar, O Lord, that I may publiſh with the voice of thankſgiving, and tell of all thy wondrous works,</hi> and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 71. 17. he profeſſeth that he hath per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed his engagement: <hi>Hitherto I have declared thy wondrous works.</hi> The Lord doth great things for this end, <hi>That we ſhew forth all his praiſe in the gates,</hi> Pſal. 9. 13, 14.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. Talk then of his great doings for us publickly, with all ſolemn commemorations and confeſſions: Let Parents declare it to their children: If thy Son ask thee, ſaying, What is this, and what meaneth theſe things, thou ſhalt declare it fully unto him, as ye have the like commanded, <hi>Exod.</hi> 13. 14. and <hi>Joſh.</hi> 4. 5, 6, 7. the Pſalmiſt promiſed, <hi>to make known Gods works to the generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to come,</hi> 78, 4. 6, 8. hide not then theſe things from others, but ſay as the Lepers, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 7. 9. <hi>This day is a day of good tidings, we do not well to hold our peace,</hi> write them in your memories, and open them in your communications; he is a ſon of <hi>Belial</hi> that doth it not. Take theſe motives to enforce the Duty. 1. Thereby we advance Gods glory; the work-man is exalted,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:34685:22"/> when the work is commended. 2. Thereby we teſtifie our own thankfulneſſe to God, and gives the glory of all to him. 3. We provock and encourage others to the like performance; <hi>I will make thy name to be remembred</hi> (ſaith the Pſalmiſt) <hi>in all genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, therefore ſhall the people praiſe thee,</hi> Pſal. 45. 17. <hi>Moſes</hi> told <hi>Jethro</hi> all that the Lord had done for his people, and <hi>Jethro</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, <hi>bleſſed and magnified the Lord,</hi> Exod. 8, 9, 10, 11. 4. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we engage our ſelves and encourage others to a right Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of Gods works, that we neither contemn nor abuſe them, but take them with all dutifull reſpect and ſubmiſſive re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence out of Gods own hand, and entertain them as his gifts and doings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. Blame worthy then are they; Firſt, who by their ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſilence conceales theſe great doings. Conſcience of former guiltineſſe, choaks and ſhuts the mouths of ſome, they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded and lay their hand upon their mouth. But ſecondly, Much more guilty and blame worthy are others, who like the dog in the manger will neither commemorate Gods doings them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, nor ſuffer others to do it: Or, thirdly, Who ſtands fretting within, and gnaſhing the teeth while they behold others about it; but theſe, as it was told before, <hi>ſhall be aſhamed and confounded for their envie,</hi> Iſa. 26. 11.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſ.</hi> 5. <hi>Gods people ſhould not only notice and declare Gods great doings, but alſo apply them:</hi> ſo did the Jews here, and therein lay the difference betwixt the heathen and them; for the Heathen could lay no claim to them, nor had intereſt in them; they could not appropriate, becauſe they were not done for them, but for the <hi>Jews</hi> they were done; they therefore had intereſt in them, and rightly laid claim to them. Thankfull ones are ſtill applying and takes Gods doings as his gifts given to them, and done for them. And it is to be marked that their application was univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall, they did it as one man with one mouth and heart, and as all concerned in it. Search the Scriptures and ye will find the Lords people upon the receipt of common favours done to the body, each of them laying claim to the ſame, as a ſharer therein, and counting it done as for all in common, ſo for himſelf in particular. When they were delivered out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and poſſeſſed in <hi>Canaan,</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:34685:23"/> or freed from their enemies, or bleſſed with a good King, they accounted theſe done to all in common, and to every one in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular: and if any one did otherwiſe, he is branded as a ſon of <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lial,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10. 27. and looked upon as unworthy of fellowſhip or protection, but worthy of death, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11. 12.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. Look then upon theſe late Tranſactions and Revoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as Gods doings done for us, and not againſt us; they are of common concernment, and great mercies, and ſhould accordingly be entertained by all and every one of us, will ye but reveiw the great things formerly mentioned, and pauſe a little in your me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations, and conſider the great evils we are delivered from: Church evils, and State evils, and the great bleſſings beſtowed upon both Church and State, and ye will find that every true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant and honeſt Patriot is ſo great a ſharer therein, that he may truly ſay, <hi>The Lord hath done great things for us;</hi> take but one under your cogniſance, to wit, the reſtitution of our King to us: a King, the rightfull Heir of theſe Kingdoms, indued with ſo many gifts and graces, owned by the Lord, perfected by ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and made glorious by ſo many wonderfull deliverances. A King whom the Scripture calls our Father for His Fatherly love and care, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24. 11. and our Head, for His beneficial Influences, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28. 44. Our ſhepherd, to lead and defend us, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 44. 28. Our Nurſing Father, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49. 23. The breath of our noſtrils, <hi>Lam.</hi> 4. 20. The great tree under whoſe ſhadow we dwell, <hi>Dan.</hi> 4. 12. Our light, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21. 17. The Miniſter of God for our good, <hi>Rom:</hi> 13. 4. and doth not theſe work ſo ſtrongly upon us, to cry out and ſay, <hi>The Lord hath done this great work for us whereof we are glade.</hi> Are we not his Children, and he our Father? we his members, and he our Head; we the ſheep of his paſture, and he our ſhepherd. Have we not ſeen already the firſt fruits of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration: Let us therefore as one man ſay and ſing it over again, <hi>The Lord hath done many great things for us,</hi> and this in particular, in reſtoring to us our King, <hi>whereof we are glad.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. Far be it then from any, I hope there is none here to forbear to make application of Gods great doings of late as done for us: And if there be any ſuch, I muſt tell them that it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:34685:23"/> either, 1. From ignorance of the bleſſings beſtowed, and of the miſeries from which we are freed: Or, 2. From beaſtly ſtupidity, being inſenſible of good or evil: Or, 3. From pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice: Or, 4. The want of Grace: Or, 5. Needleſſe fears: Or, 6. Malice and deſperate oppoſition to the work of God: Or, 7. Envie, and ſuch like. There is none in whom there is any ſpark of Grace, or affection to his Countrey, and love to the Church of God and his Soveraign, that can forbear to ſay it over and again, <hi>The Lord hath done great things for us, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſ.</hi> 6. <hi>Great and real favours and deliverances ſhould work a great and real joy;</hi> The word rendred <hi>glad,</hi> Imports ſo much. They wrought ſo upon the <hi>Jews</hi> here, their hearts were glade, their mouths were filled with laughter, and their tongue with ſinging. Our joy ſhould in ſome meaſure be anſwerable to the ground of it: the receipt of a man-child brings great joy to the Mother, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16. 21. A clear and calm morning, after a dark and ſtormy night brings joy to the birds of the air that they creep and ſing; the Child and Wife, exults at the return of the Parent and Husband after a long abſence; and the poor captive being ſet at freedom rejoyceth with joy unſpeakable; and ſhould not a Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on rejoyce and exult, when after many and ſore pangs and troubles under miſery, when after a long and dark night of calamity, when after long pantings often deſired, but withholden comforts; the Lord comes with both his arms full of bleſſings, and cleares up a fair Sun-ſhining day of proſperity, and knocks off the Fetters and delivereth a fainting people from all their miſeries, and ſmiles upon them, and ſatisfieth their longing deſires, and ſits down in the midſt of them, and biddeth them live in his ſight: Sure theſe muſt quicken the heart and fill it with joy glorious and abundant. Promiſes of good things rejoyceth the heart, and chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the ſpirit; how much more (ſuppoſe ye) when they are turned to deeds and fulfilled? If the promiſe have ſuch an Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, then how much more when perfected and enjoyed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. Let us reſolve the Doctrine into practice to day, and with glad hearts and joyfull lips ſing, <hi>This is the day which the Lord hath made, let us rejoyce and be glad in it,</hi> and ſay, <hi>Bleſſe the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:34685:24"/> Lord, O my ſoul, and all that is within me, bleſſe his holy Name, bleſſe the Lord my ſoul, and forget not all his benefits, &amp;c.</hi> Pſal. 103. 1, 2. <hi>And ſay, O give thanks unto the Lord, for he is good: for his mercy endureth for ever: Who remembered us in our low eſtate, and hath redeem'd us from our enemies; for his mercy endureth for ever,</hi> Pſal. 136. 1. 23, 24. <hi>We will ſing, and praiſe thy power, O Lord,</hi> Pſal. 21. 13. But let us take heed that our joy fall not ſhort of the Jews joy; let us endeavour to reſemble them in it: 1. Let it be great like theirs, and like the joy of the people when <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> was anointed, after whom they piped with pipes, and rejoyced with great joy, ſo that <hi>the earth rented with the ſound of them,</hi> 1 King 1. 4. Secondly, Let our joy be full: <hi>Let our heart be glad and our glory rejoyce,</hi> Pſal. 16. 9. Thirdly, Let it be ſincere and cordial; ſaying, <hi>My heart is fixed, O God, my heart is fixed, I will ſing and give praiſe,</hi> Pſal. 57. 7. Fourthly, Univerſall, like the joy of <hi>Iſrael</hi> upon their deliverance from <hi>Egypt,</hi> and of the people at <hi>Solomons</hi> Coronation, when <hi>All</hi> rejoyced, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 2. 4. Fifthly, Manifeſt, the <hi>Jews</hi> were not aſhamed to publiſh their joy. God was not aſhamed to have done theſe great things for us, but did them with delight in the open view of men and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and ſhall we be aſhamed to publiſh our joy with loud accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations. Sixthly, Conſtant, not for a flaſh: The <hi>Jews</hi> deſires to perpetuate their joy: And ye may obſerve in the <hi>Pſam,</hi> joy upon joy, and joy after joy, and ſuch ſhould our joy be: rejoyce continually; let not the memorial of it become weariſome to us, like <hi>Iſraél</hi> whoſe praiſes and prayers ended almoſt aſſoon as they paſſed the Red-ſea, within three dayes turning their melody unto murmuring, <hi>Exod.</hi> 15. 24. <hi>They ſong his praiſe, but they ſoon forgot his works,</hi> Pſal. 106. 12, 13. Be ever ready to embrace all freſh occaſions whereby our ſlumbering affections may be awakned; and pray, <hi>That the Lord wilt not only make us glad, according to the dayes wherein he hath afflicted us; but that we may r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>joyce and be glade all our dayes,</hi> Pſal. 90. 14, 15. Seventhly, Let our joy be chiefly ſpiritual, ſinging Pſalms, Jam. 5. 13. <hi>Speaking in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſalms and Hymns, and ſpiritual Songs, ſinging and making melody in our hearts to the Lord,</hi> Eph. 5. 19. <hi>ſinging praiſes to the name of the</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:34685:24"/> moſt high, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 92. 1. and 98. 5. Let no drunken ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>all, or rant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing joy be once heard or ſeen which will but provock the Lord: Remember the Statute among the <hi>Jews</hi> upon their deliverance from <hi>Haman,</hi> to keep dayes of feaſting, and to remember the poor, <hi>by ſending them gifts,</hi> Eſth. 9. 22. Eightly, Let our joy be practicall and ſtrongly influentiall upon our lives; follow after holineſſe of Converſation, which is a reall Thankſgiving. <hi>Who can utter the mighty acts of the Lord</hi> (ſaith the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal</hi> 106. 2) <hi>Who can ſhew forth all his praiſe?</hi> and he ſheweth in the 3. verſe the beſt way to do it, is <hi>to keep Gods Judgements, and do righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe at all times:</hi> ſeeing the Lord hath done ſo great things for us, break not his Commandements any more, leaſt he be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry with us and conſume us, <hi>Ezra</hi> 9. 14.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. What ſhall we think and ſay then of theſe in whom theſe great doings of the Lord produceth no real joy; but through the corruption of their hearts occaſions theſe following evils. Firſt, Sorrow and indignation, like <hi>Haman</hi> grieving at the ſafety and advancement of <hi>Mordecai;</hi> or like <hi>Athalia</hi> renting their hearts with indignation, becauſe of <hi>Joaſh</hi> his advancement to his own, and his Fathers Throne, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 11. 14. <hi>The wicked ſee it and be grieved, he gnaſheth his teeth and melts away,</hi> Pſal. 112. 10. Secondly, Envie like <hi>Sheba,</hi> fretting againſt the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of <hi>Davids</hi> reduction, and againſt <hi>David</hi> himſelf, and turning away <hi>Iſrael</hi> from owning him, becauſe he had not the chief hand in calling him home, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20. 1, 2. Thirdly, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, <hi>Mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 7. 16. being confounded to ſee their power and glory to vaniſh into ſmoak. Fourthly, Fained ſubmiſſion bowing down with their faces towards the earth, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49. 23. and licking the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a ſerpent, <hi>Micah</hi> 7. 17. Fifthly, Counterfeit joy like <hi>Shimei,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19. 18, 19, 20. or <hi>Rufus</hi> (of whom <hi>Tacitus</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, lib. 2) who came to <hi>Vitellius</hi> after his Victory, <hi>Laetiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vultu <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>; at animo anxius,</hi> Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiting joy, yet with rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ning hearts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rinding and grieving: theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ming to themſelves the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> tongues to ſpeak the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:34685:25"/> language of <hi>Canaan</hi> in thankſgiving but it is of no price with God who weigheth the heart.
<q>
                  <l>As dale of death ſo do I hate that kind</l>
                  <l>Whoſe heart from mouth, whoſe tongue diſſents from mind.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> If any ask, how ſhall I know ſuch? And ſecondly, What be the reaſons of it? <hi>Anſw.</hi> To the firſt it is anſwered, they may be known, Firſt, by their countenance: <hi>Ex triſtitia cordis ſequitur triſtitia oris,</hi> ſaith <hi>Gregory</hi> on the place: a ſad countenance diſcovereth the want of joy. Secondly, If men have learned the arte of diſſimulation, and not ſo ingenious as the former, they may be diſcouered by a quavering voice, a tremblying note, or ſome ſuch thing, while they are ſpeaking of theſe great tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Or, Thirdly, ſome word falls through inadvertancy from their lips that beſpeaketh their ſorrow and anguiſh of heart. Or, Fourthly, Qualifications and reſerves in their ſpeaking and praying or preaching, crying up and crying down with the ſame breath, now <hi>Hoſanna,</hi> then <hi>Crucifie</hi> in the neck of it; as for example, <hi>God ſave the King, if he be for this or that,</hi> elſe, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The reaſons why men are not really glad, are 1. Miſapprehenſions and Jealouſies, ſome being void of charity, that thinks no evil, but of diſpoſition ſuſpecting the worſt, and interpret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all to the worſt, and therefor fear poſſeſſing their hearts choaks their joy. 2. Deep rooted malice, having contracted a habite of hating Kingly Government, the King and the Royal Family, and inured their tongues to revile it and Him, therefore are tormented to ſee that Government re-eſtabliſhed, and the King reſtored. 3. Old guiltineſs, being guilty of ſo execrable wrongs, that although <hi>Shimei</hi> like they anticipate others, and profeſſe ſubjection yet their guilty conſciences doth ſo affright them, ſtill fearing <hi>Shimei</hi>'s re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, that ſtill echoes in their ears, had <hi>Zimri</hi> peace that ſlew his Maſter. 4. Envie choaks the joy of ſome, others being chief in the Imployment in bringing home the King, and turning away our captivity, and ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> like to be chief in Thanks, Honour, and Reward: This <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ſo ready to revolt when <hi>Sheba</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:34685:25"/> blew the trayterous Trumpet, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20. becauſe they thought the men of <hi>Judah</hi> would have the greateſt thanks for bringing King <hi>David</hi> back, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19. 5. Covetouſneſſe, men ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e gained on the Kings Revenues and Church Patrimony, by the c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ft of pulling down Kings, they have their wealth and places of Truſt, and by the Kings reſtitution they ſee their gain in danger; and therefore <hi>Demetrius-</hi>like, <hi>Acts</hi> 19. 24. they are full of wrath 6. Love to their opinions, luſts and fancies, like little Children who deſire not their Father may recover, that without controle they may run up and down: They fear the Kings bands and cords will ty them too ſtraitly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Concluſion.</hi> But I hope there is none ſuch here; ye have been better inſtructed in the principles of obedience and loyalty by my Reverend Father now with the Lord, once your Paſtor; whoſe Doctrine and loyall Converſation (notwithſtanding of his remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vall from you) ye have lively expreſſed in all theſe Revolutions; And therefore let us all rejoyce in our Kings ſalvation, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 20. 5 and pray, <hi>Save Lord the King, and let him hear us when we call,</hi> Pſal. 20. 9. Let the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity</hi> ſay, <hi>O give thanks unto the Lord, for he is good: for his mercy endureth for ever,</hi> Pſal. 118. 1. Let Old <hi>Aberdeen</hi> and the Pariſh ſay, <hi>The Lord hath done great things for us, whereof we are glad:</hi> And bleſſe thou the Lord, O my ſoul; Let us all ſay: This is the day which the Lord hath made, we will rejoyce and be glad in it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118. 24. God ſave the King, <hi>The Name of the God of Jacob defend Him, and grant Him according to his own heart, and fulfill all his Counſel,</hi> Pſal. 20. 1, 4. Amen, and Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
